<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A preparation for the Lord's Supper to which are added Maxims of true Christianity / written originally in French, by P. Allix ; Englished by P. Lorrain.</title>
            <title>Préparation à la Sainte Cène. English</title>
            <author>Allix, Pierre, 1641-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23830</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13484565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13484565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99726</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23830)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99726)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 781:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A preparation for the Lord's Supper to which are added Maxims of true Christianity / written originally in French, by P. Allix ; Englished by P. Lorrain.</title>
                  <title>Préparation à la Sainte Cène. English</title>
                  <author>Allix, Pierre, 1641-1717.</author>
                  <author>Lorrain, P. (Paul), d. 1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brab. Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1668.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Added t.p. on p. [59]: Epictetus Christianus, or, Maxims of true Christianity. -- London : Printed for Brab. Aylmer ..., 1688.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Quotations, maxims, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A PREPARATION FOR THE LORD'S SUPPER. To which are Added, MAXIMS
OF TRUE CHRISTIANITY.</p>
                  <p>Written Originally in <hi>French,</hi> by <hi>P. Allix.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Engliſhed by <hi>P. Lorrain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the
<hi>Three Pigeons</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in
<hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="imprimatur">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>IMPRIMATUR,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Jun.</hi> 13. 1687.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Guil. Needham.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE Right Honourable The LADY <hi>MARGARET
RUSSELL.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe Your Honour,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEING to expoſe this <hi>Tranſlation</hi> to a
<hi>World,</hi> who generally have a great indifference (not to ſay
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion) for the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of OUR RELIGION, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially
<hi>That</hi> of the HOLY EUCHARIST, and have <pb facs="tcp:99726:3"/>eſpouſed
<hi>Maxims</hi> quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to <hi>Thoſe</hi> here laid down, I had
reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it would ſtand in need of a Powerful <hi>Authority</hi>
to ſupport and vindicate it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cavils and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices, that in
the minds of many may riſe againſt the <hi>Subjects</hi> it treats of. And
as I was looking about for ſuch a PATRONAGE, which (at once) might as well by
its GREATNESS au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize and commend, as by its GOODNESS ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplifie 
<pb facs="tcp:99726:3"/>and atteſt <hi>them,</hi> it was my happineſs to fix up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on YOUR
HONOUR, who is ſo ſignally and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conteſtably poſſeſt of both
theſe <hi>Advantages.</hi> This, MADAM, was the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration made me
aſpire to the boldneſs of craving YOUR ILLUSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUS NAME, to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance
theſe <hi>Papers;</hi> in conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to which, as your HONOUR will do
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt <hi>Juſtice</hi> to PIETY, ſo will it be interpreted a 
<pb facs="tcp:99726:4"/>tranſcendent <hi>Favour</hi> to, and ever acknowledged as ſuch
by,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe Your Honour,</salute> 
                     <signed>YOUR HONOUR'S moſt humbly devoted &amp; obedient
Servant, <hi>Paul Lorrain.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="preface">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:4"/>
                  <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
                  <p>THERE are three Things abſolutely requiſite for the making
of any one a Worthy and Happy <hi>Communicant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> HE muſt throughly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thoſe
Truths, the Memory whereof Our LORD deſign'd to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in the
Inſtitution of the Holy <hi>Euchariſt.</hi> For no Man can, with any
benefit, receive this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> unleſs his Spirit be filled with
the ſame Thoughts, which Our Saviour did thereby ſuggeſt to his
<hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:5"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> HE ought to have a lively Senſe of thoſe
Comforts, ariſing from a Conſideration of the Important Truths, which
CHRIST ſo clearly repreſents to us in the Celebration of this Sacred
Myſtery; for as much as our Communicating in the LORD'S SUPPER ought not only
to conſiſt in the having our Spirits poſſeſſed with the Image of
Him, who was crucifi'd for us; but in our gathering the precious Fruits, which
accrew to us by his Death.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3, and Laſtly.</hi> As it would be an extreme
Injuſtice for us to be found wanting in our Faithfulneſs, Acknowledgement,
Love and Obedience to GOD, who ſo graciouſly acquaints us with, and makes
us ſenſible of theſe Wonders of his Mercy and Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb facs="tcp:99726:5"/>towords us; ſo we may eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Neceſſity,
Reaſonableneſs, and Extent of the Duties our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Holy
<hi>Sacrament</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gages us to; which we ought, with a Religious Care, to
diſcharge, through the whole Courſe of our Lives.</p>
                  <p>NOTHING can therefore be of greater Uſe to
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> with reſpect to the Holy <hi>Communion,</hi> than to
have the great Truths, imply'd in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> diſtinctly
propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, and be made apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of thoſe delightful Comforts
treaſur'd up therein, to the end they may thereby be diſpoſed to a ready
performance of the Duties it layes upon them.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:6"/>
                  <p>THIS is my Deſign in this ſmall <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> wherein
I ſhall follow no other Method, than that juſt now hinted at; that is, I
ſhall,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt of all,</hi> endeavour to make out, that the
<hi>Euchariſt</hi> exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits the moſt weighty and Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Points of
<hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to our View.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the next place,</hi> demonſtrate, that the Meditating
upon theſe important Verities (which are frequently cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to mind by this
<hi>Sacrament,</hi> kept up in the Church) is to true <hi>Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> a
Well-Spring of inexhauſtible Comfort, and indefectible Joy.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And finally</hi> conclude, with point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at thoſe
ſeveral Duties, which this Holy Inſtitution does ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily 
<pb facs="tcp:99726:6"/>charge us with, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not neglect the ſame, but at the
pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril of our Everlaſting Ruin.</p>
                  <p>To which three things I intend to ſpeak, without entring upon
any of thoſe Controverſies, which divide <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in this
Matter; my Deſign here being not (chiefly) to oppoſe Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, but to excite
and fortifie their Devotion and Piety, who are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy acquainted with the
<hi>Truth,</hi> though they do not always duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and reflect upon
it.</p>
                  <p>GOD grant we may ſo plainly diſcover to them, the Connexion
there is between the Truths, Conſolations and Duties of <hi>OUR
RELIGION,</hi> that while they are ſeeking for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in the Meditation of
<hi>DIVINE TRUTHS,</hi> they may at the ſame <pb facs="tcp:99726:7"/>time, meet with
ſtrong and urgent Motives to apply themſelves, with all Diligence and
Perſeverance, to the Practice of True Holineſs.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99726:7"/>
                  <head>A PREPARATION FOR THE <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> THE Hiſtory of the Inſtitution of the
LORD'S S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PPER.</head>
                     <p>THE Meaning of Our LORD in his inſtituting of the
<hi>Fuchariſt,</hi> can no way be better underſtood, than by a careful
Examination of the Terms He us'd, and the Circumſtances of his
Diſcourſe.</p>
                     <p>HIS Words expreſs the Thoughts He would ſuggeſt to the
Minds of his Apoſtles, and all other Chriſtians after them; and to the end
we ſhould the better apprehend the Senſe of them, the
<hi>Evangeliſts</hi> have not only <pb n="2" facs="tcp:99726:8"/>given us a plain
Relation of his Inſtitution, but been very careful in deſcribing all the
Circumſtances thereof to us.</p>
                     <p>THEY therefore acquaint us, that JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST inſtituted
this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that ſame Night He was Betrayed, and delivered up to the
<hi>Jews</hi> by one of his Diſciples, after he had celebrated with them the
Anniverſary of their Fore-fathers Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> in
eating the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> according to the Law of God. <hi>Exod.</hi>
12.</p>
                     <p>AS to the Form or Manner which CHRIST obſerv'd in his
Celebrating the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſts</hi> agree, that
after the <hi>Paſchal Supper,</hi> He took Bread, and having given Thanks,
brake it, and diſtributed it to his Diſciples, ſaying; <hi>Take, eat,
this is my Body, which is broken for you; do this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of
me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THEN they tell us further, that Our Lord having likewiſe
taken the Cup, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Thanks, He deliver'd it to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
ſaying, <hi>Drink ye all of this; for this is my Bloud, the Bloud of the New
Teſtament, which is ſhed for you; do this as often as you drink of it in
remembrance of me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>IN a word, they intimate to us, that the Diſciples did all
drink of it, and that having ſung an Hymn, they accompany'd <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99726:8"/>JESUS to the Garden of <hi>Gethſemane</hi> on the <hi>Mount</hi> of
<hi>Olives,</hi> where after his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving endur'd a moſt Bitter Agony, He was
laid hold of, in order to be expoſed to all the Reproaches He ſoon after
ſuffered, both from the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Romans,</hi> and ſinally to
be crucify'd. Thus ending his Life by a Puniſhment, that was equally painful
and accurſed.</p>
                     <p>MOREOVER it appears, that the Deſign of our Lord JESUS
CHRIST was, That this Ceremony ſhould be in all After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages exactly obſerv'd
in his Church. This may plainly be ſeen, Firſt, From his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituting it
to that of the <hi>Paſſover,</hi> which was to continue as long as the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion laſted, as being that which took its Beginning
from the Riſe, or at leaſt the Grand Deliverance of that People. Secondly,
Becauſe this Ceremony was to be the Sacrament of a New Covenant, that
ſhould not be abrogated by any other whatſoever. Thirdly and Laſtly,
Foraſmuch as the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who had been rapt up into the
Third Heaven, there to be further acquainted with the great Myſtery of Faith,
informs the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, that they ought to declare, that is (according to the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> way of ſpeaking) to celebrate the Memory of 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99726:9"/>CHRIST's Death, untill his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, that is, to the End
of the World, when he ſhall return from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to judge both the Quick and
the Dead, in order to the Completion of his Promiſes, and our Hopes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST borrow'd the Actions
and Expreſſions HE made uſe of in the Inſtitution of the
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> from the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THERE are two ſorts of Reflections may be made upon the
Inſtitution of the <hi>Lord's Supper.</hi> Some do ſerve to explain the
Letter, and out-ſide of this Sacrament; and others, again inform us of the
great Aim and Deſign of it. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with the Firſt.</p>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99726:9"/>
                     <p>AS it is well known, that in the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of
<hi>Baptiſm,</hi> CHRIST borrowed the Rite of Waſhing, practiſed by the
<hi>Jews</hi> on thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> they admitted to the Publick
Profeſſion of <hi>Judaiſm;</hi> ſo it is as plain, that our Saviour in
the Inſtitution of his Holy Supper, did ſo far comply with the
<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Cuſtoms, after the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of their
<hi>Paſſover</hi> (yet raiſing ſome of them to a much more excellent
Senſe, than they had before) that He follow'd cloſely the Notions and
Expreſſions of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>TO clear this, we muſt know that the Evening of the
<hi>Paſſover,</hi> the Maſter of the Houſe began this Solemnity with
Praiſes to God, holding in his Hand a Cup of Wine, whereof himſelf having
firſt drunk, he gave it to all the Company.</p>
                     <p>AFTER this, inſtead of the uſual Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the
Bread, he was wont to take an unleavened Cake in his Hand, ſaying, <hi>This
is the Bread of Affliction, which our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did Eat in</hi> Egypt. Words
that had a Natural Relation to the Hiſtory of their Bondage and Deliverance
of old.</p>
                     <p>I omit the whole Ceremony of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi>
which is deſcribed in the 12th. Chapter of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and ſhall only
remark, that after this Feaſt the Maſter <pb n="6" facs="tcp:99726:10"/>of the Houſe
was us'd to take the Cup a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which at firſt he had conſecrated, and
having given thanks, to preſent it to the Participants, ſaying to them,
that That was the Fruit of the Vine, and the Bloud of Grapes. An Expreſſion
bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd from <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Chap. 49.11. and <hi>Deut.</hi> Ch.
32.14.</p>
                     <p>FINALLY, after this Ceremony, their Cuſtom was to Sing the
113th. &amp; 114th. <hi>Pſalms,</hi> as an <hi>Hymn</hi> that concluded the
Devotion of this Solemnity: Which Song of Praiſe they ſtill at this day
call the <hi>Hallel.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>'TIS evident our Lord did imitate this Uſage, which is
ſtill obſerv'd by the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſave only that they don't eat a
Lamb. When therefore He had eaten the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> He took the
Bread, which was deſigned to commemorate the Miſery the Children of
<hi>Iſrael</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and made uſe of the ſame
Bleſſing and Giving of Thanks, which was received among the <hi>Jews;</hi>
Brake the Bread He had taken; and intending this Ceremony ſhould preſerve
the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Death, He ſtill proſecuted the ſame Notions and
Expreſſions of the <hi>Jews;</hi> ſaying, that it was his Body which was
now to be broken for the Remiſſion of the Sins of Mankind.</p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99726:10"/>
                     <p>AFTER this, He (according to the Practice of the
<hi>Jews</hi>) took the Cup, gave thanks a ſecond time, and having ended his
Bleſſing or Prayer, (for theſe ſignifie the ſame thing among the
<hi>Jews</hi>) He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that this Cup was the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his
Bloud, or the Bloud of the New Teſtament by which God granted penitent
Sinners the Pardon of their Sins.</p>
                     <p>WHICH Expreſſions clearly ſhew, that He would have this
Cup to be conſider'd as a Memorial of the New Teſtament, of which he was
the Mediator.</p>
                     <p>IN ſhort, is it not manifeſt, that He, together with his
Diſciples ſang the ſame Hymns, which were ſolemn and cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with
the <hi>Jews</hi> on this occaſion?</p>
                     <p>THERE is no man who does not eaſily perceive that JESUS
CHRIST found in this conſtant Cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> a juſt ground
for expreſſing himſelf as He did, when he deſign'd to inſtitute, and
perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate in his Church a Publick Memorial of his Death and Sufferings.</p>
                     <p>THE <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, the Mortal E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies of our
Religion, do agree with this. They highly maintain, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to CHRIST's
Senſe, theſe Words, <hi>This is my Body, &amp;c.</hi> which He pronounced
in ſhewing the Bread, cannot import the <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99726:11"/>notion of Reality,
but only of Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that his Meaning was very appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, both becauſe
He ſaid in the 6th. of St. <hi>John</hi> concerning the Eating here
men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, <hi>The Words that I ſpeak to you are Spirit and Life,</hi> that
is, they are to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in a Spiritual Senſe; and becauſe it was
an uſual Expreſſion with them to ſay, <hi>This is the Bread, which our
Fathers did Eat,</hi> though indeed it was but the Memorial of it.
<hi>Fortalit. Fid. L.</hi> 3. § 11. <hi>p.</hi> 172.</p>
                     <p>Thus the Expreſſions of our Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as appears) made
up of thoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Idea's ſo current among the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is
evident that his Deſign in inſtituting of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> was to
repreſent his Death to us, as a thing, which for time to come was to be
commemorated by the Church, He ſubſtituting it in the room of the Memorial
of the Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the ancient Covenant God had made
with the <hi>Jews,</hi> after his having ſet them at Liberty from their hard
Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</p>
                     <p>BUT theſe Remarks, which only reſpect the out-ſide of
the Euchariſt, are of much leſs importance than thoſe of the Second
Order, which refer to our Lord's Deſign in his Inſtitution of this Holy
Sacrament.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99726:11"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> That JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST in his
Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> has followed Idea's or Notions,
quite oppoſite to thoſe of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb;</hi> And what thoſe
Idea's of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> are.</head>
                     <p>OUR Saviour's Words are not to be compar'd only with thoſe
the <hi>Jews</hi> made uſe of at the Eating of their Unleavened Bread, which
they call'd the <hi>Bread of Affliction,</hi> becauſe it was a
Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of it; but (that they may be throughly illuſtrated) they
are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered with oppoſition to the <hi>Idea's</hi> of the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> to which our Lord was willing to make the Celebration
of this Sacrament to ſucced. And indeed not only St. <hi>Paul</hi> leads us
naturally to look upon the Sacrifice of the <hi>Paſſover</hi> as a he
ſays 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.7. that CHRIST <hi>our</hi> Paſſover <hi>is
Sacrificed for us;</hi> nor only did JESUS CHRIST for this chooſe the time of
the <hi>Paſſover</hi> to ordain the Memorial of his Death; but the
<hi>Jews</hi> themſelves ſeem <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99726:12"/>fully to agree with it,
when they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound this, as one of their moſt ancient Traditions, That the
<hi>Meſſias</hi> is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their Salvation the ſelf ſame Day, in
which they were deliver'd from their <hi>Egyptian</hi> Bondage. <hi>Fagius ad
Exod.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                     <p>Firſt then, I ſay, that it is evident our Lord's Deſign
was to ſubſtitute the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the Deliverance of Mankind by his Death,
in the room of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the <hi>Jews</hi> Deliverance by the Bloud
of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb.</hi> He does not now command the Eating of a Lamb as
formerly; and his Words, <hi>Do this,</hi> are not at all ſpoken to that
purpoſe; but his Intent was to aboliſh the Memory of the Curſe GOD had
pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Race of <hi>Cham,</hi> which was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted in the
Death of the Firſt-born in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and had been a Principle of
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion among thoſe Nations he now unites again. It is with reſpect to
his Death (which under the Appearance of a Curſe, has made him the
Bleſſing of the World) that he ordain'd this Ceremony of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and
eating Bread. Which latter Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony CHRIST prefers before the Eating of the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> it being his Will, that it ſhould thenceforwards be
conſidered as the Chief Ceremony of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99726:12"/>as
being a ſolemn Token of his having aboliſh'd the Curſe due to Sinners;
whereof indeed the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> was a publick Monument with
reſpect to the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> though it was a Signal of God's
Bleſſing to the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>IN the ſecond place I ſay, that Chriſt expreſſes
himſelf ſo as to give us <hi>Idea's</hi> very much differing from thoſe
of the <hi>Jews.</hi> For Firſt, He ſpeaks of a New Teſtament, in
oppoſition to the Old he was about to aboliſh. Secondly, He op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes his
Bloud, <hi>Which was ſhed for many, for the remiſſion of their Sins,</hi>
to the Bloud of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> that was poured forth only for a
few, and the Ceremony of it celebrated but in one Nation, <hi>viz.</hi> that of
the <hi>Jews,</hi> to which alone the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the <hi>Egyptian</hi>
Deliverance was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate. Thirdly, He oppoſes the Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Fleſh,
which he repreſents as a Sacrifice He was about to offer up for the Sins of
the World, to the Eating of thoſe Lambs, that were ſlain in purſuance of
God's Law.</p>
                     <p>This being laid down (which I hope cannot be contradicted) it
is plain that foraſmuch as JESUS CHRIST did partly make uſe of the
<hi>Idea's</hi> or Notions of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and partly
expreſs'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99726:13"/>with oppoſition to that Ceremony,
We muſt neceſſarily, in order to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the true Meaning of
our Lord in the Inſtitution of his Supper, and having a perfect Knowledg of
it, make out a due Parallel between the <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb,</hi> that kept up
the Remembrance of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Deliverance, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the
<hi>Euchariſt,</hi> which preſerves that of the Death of our Lord and
Saviour.</p>
                     <p>In order whereto theſe following Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections may be made
upon the Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Celebration of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Firſt is, That is was God's Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in inſtituting
this Ceremony, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the Memory of ſo great and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious an Event
as that of his People's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was to all
Poſterity. This He Himſelf expreſſes in the 12th. Chapter of
<hi>Exodus,</hi> in this manner: <hi>This day ſhall be unto you for a
Memorial; and you ſhall keep it a Feaſt to the Lord through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out your
Generations: And when your Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſhall anſwer, It is the Sacrifice of
the Lord's</hi> Paſſover, <hi>who paſſed over the Houſes of the
Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>in</hi> Egypt, <hi>when He ſmote the</hi>
Egyptians, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered our Houſes.</hi> It was with regard to this,
that to excite the Curioſity of <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99726:13"/>all the People, yea, even
of the very Children, He ordain'd that they, who were to celebrate the
Paſſover, ſhould take a Journey to the Temple, in that Equipage of
Travellers, in which their Fore-fathers departed out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> He
would have them alſo eat Unleavened Bread for the ſpace of ſevendays, and
bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or wild Herbs with the <hi>Paſchal Lamb;</hi> and He (in like
manner) ordain'd, that they ſhould every year renew this Ceremony, wherein
their Children had a ſhare as ſoon as they were capable of asking their
Fathers the reaſon of all this change from their uſual way of Eating. And
indeed ſuch a Ceremony thus ſolemnly obſerved every year, and to which
every one, from one Generation to another, does by a publick Law ſubmit
himſelf, is an infallible means to eſtabliſh the Belief of a Matter of
Fact, and preſerve the Memory of great Events.</p>
                     <p>The Second is, That GOD would have his People conſider with
what exact Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, He had acquitted Himſelf of all his Promiſes,
by delivering them with a ſtrong Hand, and ſtretched-out Arm from the cruel
Power of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> at the ſame time when He made an Example of
this Barbarous Poſterity of <hi>Cham,</hi> who <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99726:14"/>had
afflicted them in a long &amp; painful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude. For as on one hand GOD had
ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted all the Progeny of <hi>Cham</hi> to his Curſe (as you may ſee,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 9.25.) which began to take Effect in thoſe Plagues wherewith He
ſmote <hi>Egypt,</hi> though it was afterwards more exactly fulfilled by the
Deſtruction of the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> So on the other He ſaid to
<hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi> 15. v. 13, 14, &amp; 16. where he explains the
promiſed Bleſſing; <hi>Know of a Surety, that thy Seed ſhall be a
Stranger in a Land that is not theirs, and ſhall ſerve them, and they
ſhall afflict them four hundred years. And alſo that Nation whom they
ſhall ſerve, will I judge; and afterwards ſhall they come out with great
Subſtance. But in the Fourth Generation they ſhall come hither again.</hi>
Behold here the Oracle that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains an Excellent Promiſe; which being made
good to the <hi>Jews,</hi> He commands them to celebrate the Memory of the
Exact Accompliſhment thereof by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Anniverſary Feſtival of
the <hi>Paſchal Lamb.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THE third Reflection we may make upon the Inſtitution of the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> in this, That God would have the <hi>Jews</hi> look on
their Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as the greateſt Bleſſing He had
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver vouchſafed to them. And certainly <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99726:14"/>as He had
expreſs'd an exceeding great Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in with-holding <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Knife
from ſlaying <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and ſubſtituting a Ram in the Room of him;
ſo there was none of the Firſt-born of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> but could
ſay, that GOD had been as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to them, as He was to <hi>Iſaac,</hi>
by cauſing the Sword of the Deſtroying Angel to fall upon a Lamb, at a time
when he was commiſſioned to ſlay all the Firſt-born in <hi>Egypt</hi>
both of Man and Beaſt.</p>
                     <p>The Fourth Reflection was hinted at juſt now, which is, That
GOD would have his People underſtand, that the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piation of the Sins of
their Anceſtors had been typify'd and prefigur'd by his accepting of the
Bloud of their Lambs, inſtead of the Lives and Bloud of their Firſt-born.
And indeed in agreement to this Obſervation we may ſay, that the whole Law
in all its ſeveral Expiations, wherein Sin was transferr'd upon the
Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, did nothing elſe but further illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and extend the Figure
of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Offering, as likewiſe that of the Sacrifice of the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and repreſent the ſame more lively and
diſtinctly to the Minds of them that Offer'd; God having joyn'd to this
Expiatory Sacrifice, certain cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99726:15"/>of Places,
Perſons, and Time, to the end the Impreſſion of it might be the deeper,
and leave a more lively Senſe in the minds of thoſe that were concern'd
therein.</p>
                     <p>A Fifth Reflection upon the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> is this,
that it was to be conſider'd as a Publick Pledge and Token of the Covenant
GOD had made with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by preferring them before
the <hi>Iſmaelites</hi> and <hi>Edomites,</hi> who were deſcended, the
former from <hi>Abraham,</hi> and the latter from <hi>Iſaac.</hi> The Sign of
Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion did ſufficiently acquaint the <hi>Jews,</hi> that by this
diſtinguiſhing Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter GOD had choſen them from among all other
Nations of the Earth, to accompliſh in the midſt of them the Promiſe He
had made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> namely, that of his Seed the <hi>Meſſias</hi>
was to be born, in whom all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhould be bleſſed: But this ſign
of Circumciſion being common to the <hi>Jews,</hi> with the
<hi>Iſmaelites</hi> and <hi>Edomites,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of both theſe to
the Priviledges of the Covenant (which GOD had firſt made with
<hi>Abraham,</hi> and afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new'd with <hi>Iſaac</hi>) was ſtill
kept up. It was therefore requiſite there ſhould be a Religious Ceremony,
that might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate that this Covenant was parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99726:15"/>confin'd within the Family of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob.</hi> Which was
done by the <hi>Paſchal Lamb.</hi> For this repreſented to them, that
(ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what was foretold <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.) Affliction, and that in
this State they had receiv'd a particular Relief and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from GOD;
which, foraſmuch as it could not be ſaid of the <hi>Iſmaelites</hi> or
<hi>Edomites,</hi> did moſt ſtrongly refute all their Pretenſions to a
Right in God's Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with <hi>Abraham.</hi> This likewiſe moſt clearly
ſet forth to them, that God by virtue of his Covenant, had, out of his Mercy,
preſerved them at a time when the <hi>Egyptians</hi> felt the Effects of his
Curſe and Vengeance, and that accordingly He would not fail of fulfilling
that Great Promiſe, in order to the accompliſhment of which He had ſo
miraculouſly preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and after him, their Fathers
alſo, from the Sword of the Deſtroying Angel.</p>
                     <p>LASTLY, It is to be obſerved, that as this Ceremony reminded
them of GOD'S Love for their Nation, of his Faithfulneſs in making good his
Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, of the Expiation of their Iniquities, and of his Covenant with
them (A Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant by which He had engaged to be <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99726:16"/>their God,
that is, their Benefactor and Protector, and one day to give them the
<hi>Meſſias,</hi> who was to be born of their Nation,) ſo it naturally
led them alſo to look upon themſelves as the People of GOD, and to obey Him
faithfully; In a word, to anſwer by a Holy Life, and all the marks of true
Gratitude, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour GOD had conferr'd upon them, by his making (out of his
meer Good Will) a Covenant with them, and calling them to ſo great Hopes, as
thoſe were, which He had ſet before them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the Truths which the Holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
repreſents to us.</head>
                     <p>THESE are the Principal Truths, great Comforts and juſt
Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to ſerve GOD religiouſly, which ſo manifeſtly were imply'd
in the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb.</hi> But how much more important
is the thing our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour has made to ſupply the place of <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99726:16"/>it in his Inſtitution of the <hi>Euchariſt!</hi> That which he
exhibits to us in this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Myſtery (whether with reſpect to the Truths,
Comforts, or our Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Piety it contains) is infinitely more Sublime,
great and real. To be aſſured of this, we need only to reſume and
attentively conſider the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned three Points. I begin with the Truths
the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> repreſents to us.</p>
                     <p>THE firſt of theſe Truths reſpects the Purpoſe and
Deſign of our Lord, when He inſtituted the Sacrament of his Supper.
Certainly it was (as all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians agree) to eſtabliſh a publick
Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of his Death, as being the greateſt Event that could ever be
commemorated. Firſt, He brake the Bread; and then, to expreſs what He meant
by this break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Bread, He ſaid, that <hi>it was his Body
broken,</hi> i. e. torn by the cruelty of his Tormenters. He preſented
after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Cup to his Diſciples; and to unfold the Myſtery thereof,
added that <hi>it was the New Teſtament in his Blood;</hi> which had a
natural reference to his Death. This He explains more clearly in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi> that is, in commemoration of my
Sufferings. Which made St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>As often as you 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99726:17"/>ſhall Eat of this Bread and Drink of this Cup, you
ſhew</hi> (or according to our way of ſpeaking, <hi>you muſt ſhew or
declare</hi>) <hi>the Lord's Death,</hi> i. e. you are to call to mind, and
ſolemnly commemorate this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful effect of the Love of God. Indeed we
ſee the Evangeliſts have ſo exactly deſcribed the Death of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> with all the Circumſtances thereof to us, that we may
aver, they have (as it were) preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us with the very Picture and Lively
Image of it. So that had we been Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſſes of the ſame our ſelves,
and in company with them upon <hi>Mount Calvary,</hi> we ſhould hardly have
been ſo well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith, as now we are. But beſides this, it was
our Saviour's will, that by a Religious Ceremony, which ſhould be
ſolemnized to the World's End, his Death might continually be placed before
our Eyes. And notwithſtanding this ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomious Death was to prove a
Stumbling-block to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and at firſt be look'd upon as meer
Fooliſhneſs by the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> yet would He have the Remembrance
thereof to be dearly preſerv'd in his Church, by his inſtituting of the
<hi>Euchariſt</hi> much after the ſame manner as God the Father had
inſtituted the Ceremony of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> which did yearly
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99726:17"/>the Memory of the <hi>Jews</hi> about their
Deliverance out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Event, that had
ever happened to their Nation.</p>
                     <p>THE ſecond Truth which the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> offers to
us, is, That <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> is the true <hi>MESSIAS</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed
by God, and that we have in Him the Accompliſhment of the ancient
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies; which (among the diverſe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters that the <hi>MESSIAS</hi>
was to be known by, and are exactly found in Our Lord) expreſly foretold that
He was to ſuffer Death. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>Iſ.</hi> 53. <hi>Dan.</hi>
9.26. And here it is well worth our while to conſider: Firſt, That GOD had
ſtampt the mark of his Curſe upon the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Croſs.
<hi>Curſed is every one that hangs on a Tree,</hi> Deut. 21.23. Gal. 3.13.
Secondly, That though GOD had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> as One who was
to be the Fountain of Bleſſings to all Nations, Tribes and Families of the
Earth; yet at the ſame time He had given forth many Oracles concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his
Death upon the Croſs, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Circumſtances of it. Thirdly, That
GOD was pleaſed to dictate a greater Number of Oracles relating to this
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than to any other of thoſe Glorious <pb n="22" facs="tcp:99726:18"/>and
wonderful Events, whereby the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> was to be diſtinguiſh'd
du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Life here. The Prophecies men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning his Birth, and the place of
his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, are but few; whereas GOD pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignifi'd by the Prophets, and
repreſented by manifold Lively Types and Figures 1. <hi>That both</hi> Jews
<hi>and</hi> Gentiles <hi>were to joyn together in the Deſtroying of the
MESSIAS,</hi> Pſal. 2.1. 2. <hi>That his own Diſciple, and one that ate
Bread with him ſhould betray him.</hi> Pſal. 41.9. 3. <hi>That He ſhould
be ſold for thirty Pieces of Silver,</hi> Zach. 11.12. 4. <hi>That his
Diſciples would forſake Him,</hi> Zach. 13.7. 5. <hi>That He was to be the
ſcorn and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Adverſaries,</hi> Pſal. 22.7. 6. <hi>That He
ſhould hold his Peace as a Sheep dumb before his Tormenters,</hi> Iſa.
53.7. 7. <hi>That the Great Men of the World were to take Council together for
putting Him to Death.</hi> Pſal. 2.2. 8. <hi>That He was to be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as
an Object of Horror and Deteſtation,</hi> Iſa. 53.3. 9. <hi>That He was to
be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among Tranſgreſſors,</hi> Iſa. 53.12. 10. <hi>That they
ſhould pierce his Hands and Feet,</hi> Pſal. 22.16. 11. <hi>That Lots
ſhould be caſt upon his Veſture,</hi> Pſal. 22.18. 12. <hi>That He
ſhould be inſulted over, and derided on the account of his truſting in
God,</hi> Pſal. 22.8. 13. <hi>That he was to complain <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99726:18"/>of
his being abandoned by GOD to the fury of his Enemies,</hi> Pſal. 22.1. 14.
<hi>That they would give Him Gall and Vinegar to drink,</hi> Pſal. 69.22. 15.
<hi>That He was to commit his Soul into the Hands of GOD,</hi> Pſal. 31.5.
16. <hi>That his Side was to be pierced with a Spear,</hi> Zach. 12.10. 17.
<hi>That none of his Bones ſhould be broken,</hi> Exod. 12.49. Pſal. 34.20.
18. <hi>That He ſhould be laid in a Rich Man's Tomb, Iſa.</hi> 53.9. And
beſides theſe, there a great many other Circumſtances to the ſame
purpoſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly ſpecify'd by the Prophets. But I wave them; my Deſign
being only to hint at the moſt remarkable.</p>
                     <p>WHAT I have mentioned here is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient: Firſt, to
demonſtrate, that CHRIST'S Death (with all the notable paſſages of it)
was a convincing Proof of his being the promiſed <hi>MESSIAS.</hi> But in the
ſecond place, it is yet more evident, that as our Saviour would have a lively
Senſe of his Bloody Death and Paſſion, to be preſerv'd by a publick
Monument, that might perpetuate the memory of it in his Church, ſo was He
willing thereby to inculcate the more forcibly this Proof of his being the
Meſſias. A Proof taken from the kind of Death, which He ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and
the Circumſtances attending <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99726:19"/>it. For as much as this Death
(which had ſo much Scandal in it) being the Object of the Chriſtian
Religion would inevitably expoſe it to many Reflections and the Oppoſition
of great difficulties.</p>
                     <p>THE third Truth, which the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt repreſents to us,
is, That the Paſſion of CHRIST, which the <hi>Jews</hi> look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as an
Evident Sign of the Curſe of God, is moſt truly a plentiful conveyance of
the greateſt Bleſſings to Sinners. This we are made ſenſible of, as
ſoon as we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon theſe two Things. 1. That GOD denounced his
Curſe againſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, not only when He ſaid, Gen. 3.17. <hi>Curſed
ſhall be the Ground for thy ſake,</hi> or when in Deut. 27.26. He
pronounced <hi>him accurſed, who did not continue in all the Words of the Law
to do them;</hi> But alſo by annexing this Curſe in particular to that kind
of Death which our Lord ſuffer'd; it being ſaid, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.23.
<hi>He that is hang'd is accurſed of GOD.</hi> 2. That though GOD by his
Oracles given to <hi>Abraham</hi> had promiſed, that all Nations ſhould be
bleſſed by means of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> yet He does no leſs
expreſly declare, that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was to ſuffer the
Puniſhment of the Croſs, and conſequently be under the Curſe of GOD,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 22. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99726:19"/>A man muſt
either make no uſe of his own Reaſon, or preſently infer from theſe
Truths, that the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> was to be a Bleſſing to the World, no
other way than by his being expoſed to the Curſe for a time, <hi>viz.</hi>
by undergoing an accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Death before he could ſhower down all the
Bleſſings of his Grace and Glory up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us. The <hi>Euchariſt</hi>
preſerving the Memory of our Saviour's Paſſion, natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leads us to
this Reflection. Which will be much more ſenſibly impreſs'd upon us, if
with it we joyn a view of <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST;</hi> who preſents Himſelf on
the Croſs, as a Victim offer'd for Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and his Death as a Real
Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
                     <p>THE fourth Truth, is that which is moſt diſtinctly laid
open to us in the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and Circumſtances of the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
For,</p>
                     <p>Firſt of all, <hi>CHRIST</hi> did not only inſtitute this
Ceremony after He had ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the <hi>Paſchal Lamb</hi> with his Diſciples,
which ſet before their Eyes. 1. The Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Ram, that was offer'd
up in the Room of <hi>Iſaac.</hi> 2. That of the Lambs in <hi>Egypt,</hi> for
the redemption of the Firſt-born of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> 3. The
Teſtimony of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> expreſs'd 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99726:20"/>in theſe Terms; <hi>This is the Lamb of God, who takes
away the Sins of the World.</hi> Which ſaying of his explains all the ancient
Types, and with one word does illuſtrate whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we read concerning the
Death of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> in the 53d. of <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> And,</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <hi>CHRIST</hi> in the Inſtitution of his
Sacrament expreſſes Himſelf alſo by way of oppoſition to the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and other Sacrifices of the Law; thereby to intimate
that the ancient Deliverance the <hi>Jews</hi> had obtained by their offering
of Lambs for their Firſt-born, was but a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of that which was to be
procur'd by his Death, and that this Death was to be conſider'd as a true
Sacrifice, by means of which GOD was certainly and fully reconcil'd to Sinners.
And this Truth it is evident CHRIST was willing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare moſt ſenſibly
to us; 1. When He repreſents his Body as broken, and his Blood as ſhed. 2.
When he wills us to eat the Bread of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and drink of the
Cup, as Eating his Body and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Blood. Indeed when Our Saviour
commanded his Diſciples, (and in their Perſons all the Faithful) to eat his
Fleſh and drink his Blood, it is manifeſt, that He would, 1. Take off the
reſtraint of the Old Law, which forbad Sinners <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99726:20"/>to eat of
the Sacrifice that was offer'd for their Sins. 2. Aboliſh that Precept of the
ſame Law, which abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned Men to abſtain from Blood. And as
this intimates that thoſe Victims of old had never made any through
Expiation; ſo it plainly ſhews, that CHRIST offer'd up Himſelf as the
true Sacrifice from which this Bleſſed Effect was to be look'd for.
Moreover after his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſuggeſted theſe Ideas of Himſelf as a Victim
ſlain, He now repreſents Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to us under the Notion of an High
Prieſt, when he ſays, Mat. 26.29. <hi>I will not drink henceforth of this
Fruit of the Vine, until that Day when I drink it new with you in my Father's
Kingdom;</hi> In which words He alludes to the Cuſtom of of the High
Prieſt, who after he had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily concluded his Solemn Sacrifice on the Day
of Atonement, and was come home ſafe from the Sanctuary (where GOD had killed
ſome) he was wont to make a Feaſt to his Friends, in token of joy, for the
good ſucceſs of his Function.</p>
                     <p>'TIS this important Truth the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſo
ſtrongly aſſerts in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews;</hi> And it is for
the ſame reaſon, that when he was deſirous to take off the
<hi>Corinthians</hi> from the Communion they <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99726:21"/>had with
<hi>Heathens</hi> in their Sacrifices, he repreſents to them the Celebration
of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as a participating of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offer'd up by
our Lord.</p>
                     <p>INDEED if this Sacrament had been inſtituted by CHRIST,
after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection (which wholly effaced the Pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traiture of his Shame
and Sufferings) it would have been much more difficult to have thence
inculcated to us this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truth of the Chriſtian Religion. But Our
Lord did expreſly chooſe the time im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately before his Death, that ſo
the Ceremony, which was to preſerve the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of it, might ſo fill us
with the ſenſe of the Shame and Puniſhment he endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it might
lead us to make a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Reflection upon theſe Truths, <hi>viz.</hi> That
when JESUS CHRIST dy'd; He dy'd for Sinners; That when He was nail'd to the
Croſs, He bore their Sins in his Body on the Tree; That when He was wounded,
it was for our Tranſgreſſions; and that by his Stripes we are healed.</p>
                     <p>THE fifth Truth, which our Saviour was willing continually to
ſet before our Eyes by the Celebration of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> is, That
this Bloody Death of his was the Bleſſed Means, by which GOD entred into
Covenant with Mankind. <hi>Moſes</hi> 
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99726:21"/>had ſaid of the
Blood he ſprinkled upon the People, <hi>Behold the Blood of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
which the Lord has made with you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all theſe words, Exod.</hi>
24.8. And Our Saviour plainly oppoſing his Blood to that, ſays concerning
the Cup, <hi>This Cup is the New Covenant</hi> (or <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>)
<hi>in my Blood, which is ſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of your Sins.</hi> This
Covenant is the greateſt and moſt important Truth of our Religion. By it
GOD delivers Men from Hell, and reſtores them to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and Protection.
It is this alſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plays before us the whole Myſtery of our Redemption;
as 1. That Man being created Innocent fell into Rebellion againſt GOD, by
liſt'ning to the inſinuations of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. 2. That though Man deſerved
to be not only reduc'd to nothing, from whence the Hand of GOD had raiſed him
at the firſt, but to be caſt into Hell, there to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the puniſhment
due to his Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; yet GOD being mov'd with pity, reſolv'd to
forgive all, and make a New Covenant with him. 3. That it was the Will of GOD
that <hi>his Own Son</hi> taking in due time Human Nature upon Him, ſhould be
the Perſon in whoſe Blood this Covenant was to be Eſtabliſhed. 4. That
JESUS CHRIST having really ſhed <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99726:22"/>his Blood, this Covenant
was fully rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd and confirmed, and Remiſſion of Sins offer'd to all
that would repent. For that is the thing which is meant by the New Covenant,
according as GOD expreſſes it in <hi>Jeremy</hi> 31.34. ſaying, <hi>I
will forgive their Iniquity and remember their Sin no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THE ſixth conſiderable Truth is, That our Saviour would
have us always to bear in mind his Laſt Coming to judge the World, and
conſummate the Work of Our Redemption. Accordingly this Sacrament contains
ſolemn Marks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the fulfilling of the Promiſes God had
made to ſend the <hi>Meſſias</hi> into the World. It ſets forth in what
man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner He began to act and ſuffer for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind. But He being to continue but
a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle while here upon Earth, and to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up to Heaven, there to remain
to the End of the World, this Ceremony ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaints us, that He is then to come
again from thence, in order to fulfil our Hopes, by cauſing us to reap the
laſt Fruits of his Expiation of Our Sins, that is, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Death, by
a glorious Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and making us to live for ever with GOD, a Life
that neither Sin, nor Death (which Sin has brought into the World) 
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99726:22"/>can ever diſturb. And it may be ſaid, that as the
firſt Coming of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was the great Object of the
Religion, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and Hopes of the <hi>Jews, Art thou</hi> (ſay they)
<hi>He that ſhould come, or do we look for another? Mat.</hi> 11.3. as
likewiſe of the Promiſes of Bleſſings which GOD had made to the
<hi>Gentiles</hi> themſelves, He being called <hi>the Expectation and
deſire of all Nations; Hag.</hi> 2.7. ſo is his ſecond Coming the great
Object of the Chriſtian Religion. <hi>This ſame JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> (ſaid the
Angels to his Diſciples, gazing up to Heaven) <hi>who is taken up from you
into Heaven, ſhall ſo come in like manner as you have ſeen Him go into
Heaven, Act.</hi> 1.11. On this account alſo the Church is repreſented to
us (Rev. 22.17.) calling for her Bridegroom. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride
ſay, Come. And let him that hears, ſay, Come.</hi> And indeed as the
Prophets deſcribe theſe two Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> under the
notion of one ſingle Object; ſo we ſee, that according to the mind of St.
<hi>Paul</hi> (who aſſigns for the continuance of this Holy Ordinance the
whole Interval of time to the end of the World and Chriſt's Return.) Our
Saviour has in this Sacrament united this his two Comings, as being the
greateſt Objects of our Religion.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99726:23"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Of the Comforts the Holy Euchariſt
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſters to us.</head>
                     <p>THUS having explain'd the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Truths which the
Sacrament of the Lord's Supper engages us to meditate upon, it is very Evident
that Our Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of this Sacrament furniſhes us with moſt lively and
refreſhing Comforts, which I now come to propoſe in order, with reference
to the foregoing Truths.</p>
                     <p>FIRST then, What joy muſt we needs feel when we reflect upon
this great Event, <hi>viz.</hi> the Death of Our Saviour? Let us but compare
our Happineſs with the Condition of the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> and we ſhall
eaſily perceive how high a pitch our Joy ought to be raiſed to. St.
<hi>Peter</hi> tells us, that <hi>the Prophets have enquired and ſearched
diligently what, or what manner of time the Spirit of CHRIST, which was in them
did ſignifie when it teſtifi'd before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand the Sufferings of CHRIST and the
Glory that ſhould follow,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 1.10, 11. The Promiſes of GOD
did fill their Hearts with gladneſs, even before they <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99726:23"/>came to paſs, yea, tho' <hi>it was revealed to them, that it was not
to themſelves, but to us that they miniſtred thoſe things, which have
been declar'd to us by the Preachers of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi>
1.12. They rejoyced to ſee the Faithfulneſs of GOD in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
accompliſhment of his Promiſes. And to this purpoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi>
informs us, that the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Holy Men</hi> of old <hi>dy'd
in the Faith, not having receiv'd the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but having ſeen them afar
off, and were perſwaded of them and embraced them. Heb.</hi> 11.13. Yet all
this at a diſtance. Thus <hi>Balaam, Numb.</hi> 24.17. <hi>I ſee Him, but
not now; I behold Him, but not nigh.</hi> But 'tis our happineſs that we are
come to that Bleſſed State, which Our Saviour appropriates to his
Diſciples. <hi>We ſee thoſe things which ſo many Kings and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
Perſons deſired to ſee, and did not ſee them. John</hi> the
<hi>Baptiſt</hi> who Baptized Him, bore Witneſs of Him, and foretold his
Death; yet never ſaw it. This was an Advantage reſerved for us. His Death
is now in moſt lively Colours preſented to our View. It is Matter of Fact,
cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and indubitably atteſted. He is come down from Heaven; He has taken
our Fleſh upon Him; diſcharged the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of his Miniſtery here upon
Earth, <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99726:24"/>Sanctify'd Himſelf for our ſakes; ſuffer'd
Death, and ordained a Memorial of it, as of a thing paſt and done. They of
old had no diſtinct knowledge of the Death of the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> nor of
the kind and manner of it. All which is clearly manifeſted to us, at this
Day. And though the <hi>Jew</hi> meets with Matter of Scandal, and the
<hi>Gentile</hi> and occaſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, yet the <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
finds ſubject of the moſt exalted Joy and Comfort, in the Celebration of
theſe Holy Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
                     <p>THE Second Comfort the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> adminiſters to
the Faithful, is exceeding ſweet, and raviſhing. We can no ſooner in our
Meditations, reflect upon the fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ancient Types of the
<hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> and the Oracles of old, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Coming of the
<hi>MESSIAS,</hi> but we find the ſupport of our Faith, and a ſolid ground
for our Hope to reſt on. Who can conceive the leaſt doubt of GOD'S
performing thoſe Promiſes, the Execution of which ſeems as yet very
difficult, and at a great diſtance, ſince He has already fulfilled that of
ſending the <hi>MESSIAS,</hi> who had been ſo long looked for, during the
Courſe of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages? <hi>He ſills us with good hopes for 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99726:24"/>things to come</hi> (ſays an ancient Father) <hi>For He
who has given Himſelf to us here, will much rather do ſo hereafter,
Chryſ. H.</hi> 6. <hi>ad. Pop.</hi> And indeed, who ſees not that this
Diſpenſation of his being mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in our Fleſh, and his Death in
par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, muſt fill us with ſtrong and lively Hopes, when we addreſs
our Prayers to Him? Chriſtian, 'Tis true, thou muſt appear before GOD, but
GOD <hi>has left all Judgment to the Son;</hi> and He by partaking of Fleſh
and Blood, is become thy Brother. He ſhed his Blood, and laid down his Life
to redeem thee; He dy'd to deliver thee from that Miſery and Curſe to which
thou hadſt doom'd thy ſelf to all Eternity. Wouldſt thou be as ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
convinc'd of his tender Love and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as thou art of his Power?
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider He feeds thee with his own Blood, and is ſet forth in the Holy
Supper, as the <hi>Lamb of God.</hi> is it poſſible that this
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration ſhould not remind us of that Exceſs of Love, which
prompted Him to die for us? We ſee here not a Sheep, but the Shepheard,
giving his Life for the Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his Sheep. Where will you meet with a
Shepheard that feeds his Sheep with his own Blood? Yet JESUS CHRIST, the Great
Shepheard feeds us with his. <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99726:25"/>What may not we expect from
ſo punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al a Faithfulneſs, ſupported by a Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and
Compaſſion that is beyond all Example?</p>
                     <p>THE third Comfort, which we may reap hence, is this, That
being deliver'd from the Curſe we lay under, every one of us may now ſay to
his Soul, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn unto thy Reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord has dealt
bountifully with thee;</hi> And with St. <hi>Paul</hi> triumphantly cry out,
<hi>There is now no condemnation to them who are in CHRIST JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</hi> 'Tis
<hi>He has deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd us from the fear of Death; by means of which we were all
our Life's time ſubjects to Bondage.</hi> Before we are convinc'd of this
Truth we are in a State of Miſery, Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and Deſpair. But ſince CHRIST
has alter'd our Condition, by removing the Curſe that was againſt us, What
Peace, Joy and Comfort ought not to poſſeſs our Conſciences? If we
conſider <hi>David</hi>'s Condition before <hi>Nathan</hi> had aſſur'd
him of GOD'S Pardon, we have a lively Emblem of the lamentable Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances
in which the Sinner is, whoſe Ears always ring with the Sound of this
dreadful Sentence, <hi>Curſed is he, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues not in all the Words of
this Law to do them. Deut.</hi> 27.26. He ſees the Sword of 
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:99726:25"/>the Deſtroying Angel ready to ſtrike him. But now this
Sacrament tells him, that God has put away his Iniquities, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved the
Curſe he had ſo juſtly drawn down upon himſelf. This Religious
Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony which CHRIST has annexed to the Declaration of his Goſpel, is a
Publick Monument, that GOD hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is not only become placable, but
throughly appeaſed and reconciled to Man. He cryes to us, that our Iniquities
are pardon'd, but ſays the Sinner, what ſhall I offer to GOD to make
atonement for my offences? Shall I offer him, (as <hi>Abraham</hi> did
<hi>Iſaac</hi>) my Firſt-born for my Tranſgreſſions? And the
<hi>Euchariſt</hi> points him (as the <hi>Angel</hi> did <hi>Abraham</hi>) at
the Victim prepar'd by GOD, or rather beſpeaks him in the Words of St.
<hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt, Behold the Lamb of GOD that takes away the Sin
of the World.</hi> And then the Sinner with Joy and Exultation breaks forth, He
is, He is indeed come into the World; He has ſuffer'd Death to ſave
Sinners, whereof I am chief.</p>
                     <p>NOW, if theſe Reflections on the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt</hi>
afford ſuch Comforts to <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in general, they will more
ſenſibly affect us, when we come to conſider theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts more
diſtinctly. The Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99726:26"/>by preſerving the
Remembrance of <hi>CHRIST'S</hi> Death, obliges us more particularly to
meditate upon this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Wiſdom and Love of <hi>GOD,</hi> whereby He
has deliver'd us from our Sins, by charging them upon our Lord; who, like a
Sacrifice, was ſlain in the room of Sinners, as the Ram was in the ſtead of
<hi>Iſaac,</hi> and as the Lambs, which were killed, to redeem the
Firſt-born of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> from the Sword of the Deſtroyer.
Now as there is nothing more ſtupendous than this Subſtitution, ſo
nothing yields Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation like it. For here we ſee, 1. The Love of the
Father, who withheld the ſtroke of his Vengeance from Mankind, whereas He
deſtroy'd the Apoſtate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, without remedy. 2. The Charity of the Son,
who is become our Surety. <hi>Herein is the Love of GOD, not that we loved Him
firſt, but that He loved us. No man has greater love than this, that he lays
down his Life not for his Friend, but his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi> And yet thus far did our
Saviour's Love carry Him. He preſented Himſelf a Sacrifice to <hi>GOD</hi>
the Father. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the ſtroke that was to wound us; neither the horror
of thoſe Crimes we had committed, nor the dreadful Puniſhments that were
due to us for them, being able <pb n="39" facs="tcp:99726:26"/>to deter Him from taking
upon him our Nature and Sufferings. <hi>GOD</hi> gave him to us, that He might
be the High Prieſt of his Church. But He was not inveſted in this Dignity,
nor is repreſented as making Interceſſion in Heaven for us, neither ſet
forth as Bleſſing of us, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He has expiated our Sins, by
offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Himſelf a Sacrifice to free us from Death. <hi>Moſes</hi>'s
Wife ſeeing her Husband threat'ned with Death by the Angel for her Son's not
being circumcis'd, thought it expedient to hazard the Child's Life by an
haſty and venturous Circumciſion, that ſhe might ſecure her Husband
from the danger that hung over him. <hi>GOD</hi> in this Caſe, does
ſomething far more great and wonderful for us. He gives the Life of his own
Son to redeem his Enemies; and behold, the Son readily conſents, and yields
himſelf, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did. <hi>Lo, I come</hi> (ſays He) <hi>in the
Volume of thy Book, it is wriiten of me, I delight to do thy Will, O my
God.</hi> O Ineffable and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing Love to Mankind, who deſerved nothing, but
an Eternal Curſe!</p>
                     <p>AS it was in the Blood of Lambs, that <hi>GOD</hi> made a
Covenant with the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſo the <hi>Euchariſt</hi>
repreſenting to us in the fifth Place, that the Blood <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99726:27"/>of
CHRIST is the Ground and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the New Covenant, which GOD has made
with <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not look upon the Sacrament as the Pledge
and Seal of this Covenant, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being filled with an Exceſs of Joy and
Conſolation. For indeed, what greater Glory can be imagined, than for Man to
be admitted to a Treaty with <hi>GOD?</hi> And what an inconceivable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
is this, that <hi>GOD</hi> ſhould vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to enter into Covenant with
us? There are none but are ſenſible of the Happineſs of the
<hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in this regard. To be convinc'd of which, we need only
hear them, even at this day, ſpeaking with the greateſt Comfort, of the
Honour GOD therein has done them, notwithſtanding their total diſperſion,
and groaning un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Burthen of that Curſe, which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues and overtakes
them every where. Now, that ancient Covenant GOD has aboliſhed, as being
imperfect; but this which we commemorate, is to endure for ever. The Deſign
of the former was only to give the <hi>Jews</hi> a lively Senſe of Sin, or at
the beſt to adminiſter a Typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Expiation; whereas the latter,
<hi>viz.</hi> the New (according to the Prophet <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi>) makes a true
Atonement for Sin, <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99726:27"/>and affords a Remiſſion rightly and
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo call'd. <hi>That</hi> had no promiſes, but what concern'd a
Happineſs here on Earth; whereas <hi>This</hi> does promiſe a
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Eternal Glory.</p>
                     <p>THE greateſt Honour the Old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant did confer upon the
<hi>Jews,</hi> was this, That the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> ſhould be born of their
Blood; but the Advantage of the New, is, That the <hi>MESSIAS</hi> partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of Fleſh and Blood with the reſt of Mankind, has given his own Blood to
raiſe them to the Glory of Adoption, who ſhall believe in Him. <hi>O how
happy is the People, whoſe God is the Lord!</hi> And what does this
Expreſſion, to be the God of any one, import, but this, <hi>viz.</hi> To be
his Great and Soveraign Benefactor? Of old He was the GOD of <hi>Abraham,</hi>
but not of <hi>Loth,</hi> and his Poſterity; Of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but not of
<hi>Iſmael</hi> and his Off-ſpring; Of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but not of
<hi>Eſau</hi> and the <hi>Edomites.</hi> Now, He is the GOD of all the Earth.
But he has not made this Covenant with all the Nations of the World, ſave
only by virtue and on the Sole Account of the Blood of <hi>CHRIST.</hi> And can
we with any attention, reflect on this Truth, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to us in the
<hi>Holy Euchariſt,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feeling a Joy unſpreakable and full of 
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99726:28"/>Glory? GOD had promiſed to enter into ſuch a Covenant,
as this; and <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> deſcribes it in the 31. <hi>Chap.</hi> of his
Prophecies; Yet the Old laſted till <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> and
ſo long the Ceremonies of it were in uſe. But then comes <hi>CHRIST,</hi>
and inſtead of continuing the Celebration of the Old Covenant, which was made
in the Blood of the <hi>Paſchal Lamb,</hi> He abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates it, and in its room
ſubſtitutes the New Covenant, made in his own Blood. <hi>Do this</hi>
(ſays He) <hi>in remembrance of me.</hi> Not <hi>That</hi> which was done
before, but <hi>This: For this Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood, which is
ſhed for the Remiſſion of your Sins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>TO conclude, 'tis to be conſidered (and this is the laſt
Vein of Comfort hid in the <hi>Euchariſt</hi>) that this Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
inviting us to take a View of <hi>CHRIST'S</hi> ſecond Coming, as well as of
his Diſpenſation in the Fleſh, 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but it muſt fill
our Souls with ſurpaſſing Joy and Comfort. The full Salvation of
Believers does, as yet, only conſiſt in Hope. GOD indeed pardons their
Sins; but they are ſtill ſubject to all the Miſeries Sin has brought into
the World. They hope for Eternal Life; and yet dye like other Men. Their Bodies
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99726:28"/>are laid in the Grave, and become the food of Worms. So
that their Expectation ſeems to be quite fruſtrated. And as the
<hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> find Matter of Scandal and Deriſion in
the Death of the <hi>Son</hi> of GOD, ſo according to all outward
ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, they have the ſame reaſon to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult over the Faith and Hope
of his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, when they compare theſe with their preſent Condition,
which to the Eye, differs not from that of other Men. But all theſe dark
Clouds ſhall at laſt be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd; theſe Shadows vaniſh, and <hi>the
Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Lord and his Faithful be revealed. He ſhall appear from Heaven
in the Glory of his Father, and every Eye ſhall ſee Him, even they who have
pierced Him.</hi> And as He will thus diſplay his Majeſty in the Sight of
all the World, ſo will He at the ſame time unvail the Life and Glory of his
Children, who at preſent are ready to ſink under the burthen of Sin, the
Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of <hi>CHRIST</hi>'s Adverſaries, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of the World, and
the Devil, and the Power of Death, which is the laſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of CHRIST and his
Church. <hi>He that eats my Fleſh and drinks my Blood has Eternal Life, and I
will raiſe him up at the laſt day. Whoſoever eats of this Bread ſhall
live for ever.</hi> Theſe are our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99726:29"/>Promiſes,
wherein as He terms the Embracing of Him by Faith, an Eating of his Fleſh, in
oppoſition to the Type of <hi>Manna;</hi> So this Eating may be as truly
aſcribed to them, who by Faith conſider Him, as the Sacrifice that has
taken away the Puniſhment due to Sin. O what comforts do ariſe to the
Faithful from the Expectation of this his Return! What exulting Joys will they
be filled with at his Coming! What Delights flow in upon them as they mediate
hereon! What raviſhing Pleaſures does it afford us amidſt the greateſt
Evils of this Life! What quiet in the ſharpeſt Trials! And what Confidence
even at the time when Death ſtares us in the Face!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>
                        <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of the Duties preſcribed to us in the
Holy Euchariſt.</head>
                     <p>I SUPPOSE I have very clearly made out, that it is
impoſſible atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to conſider the Truths, which the 
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99726:29"/>Lord's Supper diſcovers to us, without reaping the
unſpreakable Comforts which ſo naturally ſpring from it. And it may (with
as much Eaſe) be demonſtrated, that theſe Truths indiſpenſably engage
us to the moſt Eſſential Duties of our Religion; and that GOD having
comprehended what is moſt capable to adminiſter the ſweeteſt
Conſolations to our Souls, in this Myſtery, it cannot but at the ſame
time be very influential towards Sanctification and a Godly Life. To the making
out of which I deſign the Concluſion of this Treatiſe, where I intend to
repreſent theſe Duties, as the neceſſary and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſequents of
what I have before laid down. It behooves every Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant ſeriouſly to
conſider of theſe En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements; And the rather, becauſe this is a ſure
way for them to know whether they have worthily receiv'd the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or to
amend the faults by them committed in any preceding Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for want of
diſcharging theſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious performances as they ought.</p>
                     <p>FIRST then, Is it poſſible that a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi>
who knows that JESUS CHRIST deſigned the Celebration of the
<hi>Euchariſt</hi> for a publick Monument of his Death, as of a moſt Signal
Event, <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99726:30"/>worthy of all Commemoration, ſhould expreſs any
neglect of, or indifference for this Sacred Feaſt? The Primitive Church
called the Faithful to it every Lord's Day, looking upon the partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this
Holy Sacrament, as a Publick Profeſſion of our Faith, and the very Badge of
Chriſtianity. And ſhall our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſneſs and coldneſs in Religion be
a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Excuſe for our abſenting our ſelves from the Lord's Table, when
He him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf invites us to it, and affords us op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities for it? Some
perhaps will fancy that they have a juſt pretence to abſtain from
Receiving, becauſe of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences or Law-ſuits they are engaged in. But if
CHRIST debars them his Table, who are ſo unkindly diſpoſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their
Neighbours, does not He teach us withal, and point us at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy that is to
be found for the Cure of ſuch Uncharitableneſs? He tells us, in this
Caſe, that he who is about to offer, <hi>muſt leave his Gift before the
Altar, and go and firſt be reconciled to his Brother, and then come and offer
his Gift, Mat.</hi> 5.24. And why this? But to teach us, that we muſt either
wholly renounce our Religion, or elſe put our ſelves upon faithful
En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to obey the Laws of it; That <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99726:30"/>a Profeſſion
of Chriſtianity is both Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and impious, which is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied
with a Practice of the Duties it preſcribes; and that it is impoſſible
for a Man, with any fruit or benefit, to perform the publick Requirings of it,
while its moſt important Precepts and Rules are neglected.</p>
                     <p>SECONDLY, let it be obſerv'd, That ſince Chriſtians look
upon the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> as a convinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proof of
the Truth of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (it being a publick Memorial of Our Saviour's
Death, which was a moſt ſignal fulfilling of GOD's Promiſes, and an
E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident Character, whereby CHRIST was to be known for the true
<hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi>) they cannot but find a Natural Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation incumbent on
them to become <hi>Chriſtians</hi> indeed. The Sacrament of Baptiſm is
conferr'd upon us at a time when we know not the Nature of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements we
enter into, nor the Juſtice and Extent of the Promiſes made in our behalves
therein. But he who receives the Lord's Supper, ratifies before GOD and
<hi>Man,</hi> the Promiſes made in his Name at his Baptiſm. And this he
does in his own perſon, as ſuppoſing he has now ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently examined
the Truth of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99726:31"/>on he profeſſes. He is
ſatisfy'd that his Parents have done him the greateſt kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
imaginable, by engaging him in GOD's Service from his moſt tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy;
and that they did well to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate him to it for ever, ſince it is in
this Profeſſion his whole Happineſs conſiſts; and he now ſolemnly
renews the Oath of his inviolable Obedience and Faithfulneſs to GOD, which
before he had done by his Sureties. Can we thus reflect upon the Participation
of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> and not conceive a moſt ſenſible ſorrow
for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving acted contrary to the <hi>Laws</hi> of CHRIST and Our own
<hi>Hopes?</hi> Can we entertain this Notion of it, and not reſolve for the
time to come; more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to purſue Our Heavenly Calling, and more
exactly anſwer the Holy Deſign of the Religion we profeſs? Certainly it
is againſt Common Senſe to pretend to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and yet to
live like a <hi>Jew,</hi> or <hi>Heathen.</hi> It is ridiculous, outwardly to
acknowledge Laws more Holy and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, than thoſe the World is governed by,
and at the ſame time to follow the Cuſtoms and Manners of Worldly Men. All
the Vices of the Age ought to find their Death in this Reflection, as they do
their Condemnation in the ſacred Laws <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99726:31"/>and Religion of Our
Lord and Saviour.</p>
                     <p>WE come now to a third Reflection upon the Holy Communion,
which is no leſs plain and natural than the foregoing, <hi>viz.</hi> That in
this Sacrament we conſider the Death of CHRIST, as the Source of that
Bleſſing GOD had promiſed, and the Principle of all thoſe He will
hereafter impart to us. This Notion ſets before our Eyes the Curſe we
ſhould inevitably have fallen under, had not GOD rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it. Can any one
ſeriouſly think of this Truth, without praiſing God with all the Power of
his Soul, and returning the Fruits of a juſt acknowledgement to Him for the
ſame? O how dreadful a thing it is, to be accurſed of GOD! <hi>Go ye
Curſed into Eternal Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> And on
the contrary, how tranſporting and full of Comfort it is, to be bleſſed
by Him. JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST, the Bleſſed of GOD, has bleſſed us with all
manner of Bleſſings. He became a Curſe for us, that we might be made a
Bleſſing of God in Him. <hi>Come</hi> (ſayes He) <hi>Ye Bleſſed of my
Father.</hi> And by what other means can we be raiſed to this Bliſs, but by
the Study and Practice of Holineſs? It was the Unhappineſs of the
<hi>Jews</hi> to fancy, that all ſhould partake <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99726:32"/>of GOD'S
Promiſes to <hi>Abraham,</hi> who were deſcended from him after the
Fleſh. But the Goſpel acquaints us with theſe three Things. 1. That Faith
in CHRIST is the means GOD has appointed to make the <hi>Heathens</hi>
partakers of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. 2. That the Profeſſion of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in
CHRIST is vain, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful, where it is unaccompanied with an Holy Life.
<hi>Faith without Works is Dead.</hi> It is but a pretended and falſe
Profeſſion. 3. And Laſtly, That JESUS CHRIST will never own any for the
Bleſſed of his Father, but ſuch as by their Works of Charity and
Perſeverance in Godlineſs, ſhall have made good the Sincerity of their
adherence to his Religion.</p>
                     <p>TO this we are further engaged by a fourth Reflection, which
we make upon the Father's giving his own Son for a Sacrifice to expiate our
Crimes. Here we ſee on one hand, the Extream <hi>Averſion</hi> GOD has for
<hi>Sin,</hi> while on the other, we diſcover the infinite <hi>Love</hi> He
expreſſes to <hi>Sinners.</hi> We have ſet before us the lively Image of
that Abyſs of Miſery into which we had been plung'd, had not GOD prepar'd
this his <hi>Lamb,</hi> who gave his own Blood and Life to redeem us. Now our
Hearts muſt be utterly obdurate and inſenſible, <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99726:32"/>not
to make a moſt ſerious reflection up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on this Hatred, GOD bears to Sin.
We behold it puniſhed in a moſt dreadful and affrighting Manner, when GOD
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd the Old World by the Deluge, and rain'd down Fire from Heaven on
<hi>Sodom,</hi> and the Cities that ſnar'd in her unnatural Luſts. Theſe
Puniſhments were Marks of his Juſtice, taking Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of Sinners. But
how infinitely more terrible is GOD'S Deteſtation of Sin, pourtrai'd in the
Death of his Dear and Only Begotten Son, whom we ſee <hi>ſmitten for our
Iniquities,</hi> and in all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward apparance <hi>forſaken of his
Father.</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> had not yet ſeen Him extended on the Croſs,
nor heard Him uttering theſe doleful Words, <hi>My God, my God, Why haſt
thou forſaken me?</hi> Yet could not he, when he ſaw Him only expoſed to
his firſt Reproaches, forbear ſhedding Tears of a true Repentance. And what
may then be expected from a Sinner, who in the Sacrament of the
<hi>Euchariſt,</hi> has all the <hi>Ideas</hi> of his Agony, Sufferings and
Death, moſt lively delineated to Him? What an irreconcilable Averſion ought
not he to conceive for his Sins? What Reſolutions ought not he to take of
leaving and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking them for ever?</p>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99726:33"/>
                     <p>AND to this we find our ſelves ſtill more
indiſpenſably oblig'd, by the Nature of this Sacrament. For, in the fifth
Place, it is (as I have ſaid before) the Memorial of CHRIST'S Blood, by
vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue whereof GOD has made a New Covenant with Sinners; In which He has
aſſured us, that He will forgive us our Sins, and beſtow the Glory of his
King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon us. But the Condition with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we cannot be made Partakers
either of the Remiſſion of Sins, or of the Glory of Heaven, is, the
Repenting of our Iniquities, and applying our ſelves to the Study of
Sanctification, to our Life's End. The Beneſit of this New Covenant is, That
God remembers our Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions no more; but the Condition He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires
of us, is, That whereas the <hi>Jews</hi> laid up his Laws in the Ark, without
ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them in their Hearts, we muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways have them written in ours, in
order to a continual Religious Obſervance of them. Now, as it is his Will,
that we ſhould daily beg of Him the Pardon of Our Sins (which plainly ſhews
He is ready to grant it us;) ſo the Only Command He lays upon us, is, That
for the time to come we ſin no more, leſt a worſe thing befall us. And
indeed is it not exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99726:33"/>unaccountable, that Men, who
would paſs for Children of GOD, ſhould live the life of Devils? That they,
who look upon themſelves as Confederates with CHRIST, ſhould continually
violate the Conditions of this Covenant? GOD reminded the <hi>Jews</hi> of
their Obligation to Holineſs, upon the account of his being their GOD.
<hi>Moſes</hi> implies thus much in the 24. Chap. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> where
the People having accepted of the Laws which he had propounded to them from
<hi>GOD,</hi> after he had wrote them in a Book, and read the ſame in the
Audience of the Congregation, they anſwer'd, <hi>All that the Lord has ſaid
will we do, and be obedient.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Moſes</hi> ſprinkled the
Blood on the People, and ſaid, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Blood of the Covenant, which
the Lord has made with you concerning all theſe Words.</hi> And ſhall
Chriſtians believe, that <hi>GOD</hi> will own them for his People, while
they remain in their Bondage to Sin? The Meaning of the Covenant we have made
with GOD, has been clearly expreſſed by a Pagan, <hi>viz. Pliny,</hi> who
in his Epiſtle to the Emperour <hi>Trajan</hi> (<hi>Lib.</hi> 10.
<hi>Ep.</hi> 97.) thus explains the Notion Chriſtians had of this Glorious
Covenant, they were enter'd into with GOD, <hi>They <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99726:34"/>bind
themſelves</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by a Sacrament or Oath, not to commit any
ſuch Crimes, as are falſly reported of them, but to abſtain from Robbery,
Theft and Adultery, to be as good as their Word, and Faithful to their Truſt,
&amp;c.</hi> He plainly ſhews, that Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers looking upon themſelves as
Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates and Parties in the ſame Covenant with GOD, baniſhed all
manner of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions from the midſt of them; And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intimates, that
as they did all eat of the ſame Bread, ſo they were of one Heart and Mind,
and united to GOD by their reſemblance of Him, and imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his
Holineſs. Now ſince that time the Goſpel is not alter'd; for its Maxims
are unchangable. Neither is it only with reſpect to the Prophecies or
Promiſes therein contained, that it abides to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, without any
poſſibility, that ſo much as one tittle of it ſhould ever fall to the
Ground; but the ſame muſt be underſtood of it, as it is the Rule of our
Life and Manners, preſcribed to us by our Lord and Maſter.</p>
                     <p>LAST of all, Since JESUS CHRIST has in this Sacrament, united
the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of his Coming in Glory to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of his Humiliation
even unto Death, will not this Conſideration moſt <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99726:34"/>naturally inſpire us with powerful Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to Piety, and an
indefatigable Perſeverance in that Fidelity we owe to Him? In commemorating
our Saviour's Paſſion, we are oblig'd to deny our ſelves, and to be ready
to lay down our Lives, whenſoever it ſhall pleaſe God to require it, in
order to the advancement of his Glory. JESUS CHRIST tells us, that he is
unworthy of Him, who is not willing to leave all to follow Him. He has given
his own Life for us, and calls us to a like Abnegation of our ſelves. They
who ſeek their own Pleaſures, deſire to be Rich: But CHRIST choſe a
Volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Poverty. They are Ambitious of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, whereas He refuſed to be
made a King. They fear Death; but He freely ſubmitted Himſelf to it. They
abhor the Croſs, that ignominious and painful way of Dying; whereas He
declined not to be Crucified. We can commit no Sin, but ſo far as we deſire
the things which He deſpiſed, or endeavour to avoid thoſe He ſo
willingly underwent. Certainly the ſight of this Example ought powerfully to
oblige us to an imitation of it. It was a Saying of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s
(<hi>Epiſt.</hi> 30.) <hi>That Men are not fitted for Martyrdom, when they
are not furniſhed for the, Fight out of <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99726:35"/>the Church's
Magazine, and that the Soul is apt to faint, when it is not ſtrength'ned by a
fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Communion.</hi> This Father was in the right, and his Reaſon for
it, is the more Solid, becauſe the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> immediately after it
has exhibited to us the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Lord's Death (which arms us
with conſtancy,) ſhews us the Reward of Believers, by ſetting before our
Eyes his Coming again from Heaven to glorify them. 'Tis this Return of our
Lord, that will prove the great Comfort of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and at the ſame
time, a dread and trouble to the Wicked. JESUS CHRIST, by thus reminding us of
his Glory, while we are meditating upon his Sufferings, does much the ſame
thing He did upon the Croſs; where he accepted of the Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the
Converted Thief, approved of the Acts of his Faith, the Marks of his Love and
Tokens of his Zeal for the Innocence and Glory of this JESUS, whom he now
look'd upon, as his Saviour. CHRIST kindly received and rewarded the evident
Expreſſions of his Hopes. But on the other hand, puniſhed the Unbelief
and Impenitence of his Companion; He aſſured the former, that he would
admit Him into his Kingdom, becauſe He ſaw in his Heart the Character of a
ſincere <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99726:35"/>Believer, and all the generous Inclinations of a
Martyr; but left the latter to the juſt deſerts of his Iniquities. A true
Penitent meets with the greateſt Comforts imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the
<hi>Euchariſt,</hi> where the Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent (who <hi>treads under foot the
Blood of the Covenant, and diſcerns not the Lord's Body</hi>) <hi>receives
his own Damnation.</hi> 'Tis abſolutely impoſſible this Sacrament
ſhould not have ſuch different Effects upon theſe two ſorts of
Communicants. For from it proceeds a Voice, that proclaims Pardon to peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
Sinners; and in it we plainly ſee the Solid Foundation of that Mercy, which
GOD will in his due time, fully diſplay; But withal we ought to take notice
it cries aloud, that we muſt enter upon the Way of Holineſs, and
perſevere therein to the End, even to Death, as JESUS CHRIST did, if we
deſire to <hi>appear with full aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance before his Throne, who is to
judge all Men at the laſt Day,</hi> and <hi>render to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one according to
his Works.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:36"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:36"/>
                  <p>EPICTETUS CHRISTIANUS; OR, Maxims OF TRUE CHRISTIANITY.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brab. Aylmer,</hi> at the three
<hi>Pigeons</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1688.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="notice">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:37"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:37"/>
                  <head>Advertiſement TO THE READER.</head>
                  <p>THERE is nothing in theſe MAX<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IMS, but what is univerſally
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd and receiv'd by the CHRISTIAN World; And though they are all ſo
very plain and evident, as not to be lyable to the leaſt Diſpute; yet it
was ſuppos'd, that a <hi>Collection</hi> of them, would not be altogether
unprofitable. 'Tis true, no Body will argue againſt them, when propos'd; Yet
it muſt be granted, there are very few that mind, and fewer that practiſe
them.</p>
                  <p>THERE be many, who fancy they are good CHRISTIANS, becauſe
they apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Outward <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Religion;</hi>
Others think they go much further, becauſe they <pb facs="tcp:99726:38"/>ſtudy thoſe
<hi>Diſputable Points,</hi> which divide CHRISTIANS among themſelves. This
<hi>Cuſtomary Devotion,</hi> or <hi>Controverſial Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> is not
chiefly That, which GOD requires of us. There is ſomething more ſublime and
ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory in the Sincere Profeſſion of Religion.</p>
                  <p>IN theſe <hi>Maxims</hi> an Eſſay is made to give an
<hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Duties</hi> to ſuch, as never have made it
their buſineſs to inform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about them. If there be any, who
object that they contain nothing but ſome very common Reflections, which are
frequently heard from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> they ought to conſider, that they
are the leſs excuſable for their ignorance of, or not practiſing
<hi>(Maxims)</hi> which would not be ſo often inculcated, were they not the
moſt Eſſential Part of <hi>Goſpel-Precepts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>THE only aim in the Method obſerv'd, and Brevity affected
here, is to make the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> more eaſily ſenſible of the
neceſſity of theſe <hi>Reflections,</hi> and the Importance of the Truths
contained in them. <hi>GOD</hi> grant, that as the <hi>Deſign</hi> in Writing
of them, was to be ſubſervient to the <hi>Salvation</hi> of Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; ſo
they may ſtir up in ſome a <hi>Deſire</hi> of employing themſelves,
with more care and fervency, about the <hi>Duties</hi> they point at.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="maxims">
                  <pb facs="tcp:99726:38"/>
                  <head>EPICTETUS CHRISTIANUS; OR, Maxims OF TRUE
CHRISTIANITY.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="maxim">
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM I.</hi> That it behooves us to have Maxims of
<hi>Piety.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>THE moſt important Duty of Man, is <hi>Piety.</hi> It is no
very great matter whether we are ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or not, in all other
Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of this Life, provided we diſcharge <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99726:39"/>well the
<hi>Duties</hi> of CHRISTIANITY; and approve our ſelves juſt and honeſt.
In ſuch Caſe we cannot miſs of being happy.</p>
                     <p>HOW great an Error is it to frame <hi>Maxims</hi> to our
ſelves, whereby to attain Skill in <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> while
at the ſame time we neglect to uſe the like Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in the concerns of
<hi>Godlineſs?</hi> No wonder therefore that ſo little Progreſs is made
in it. Is it poſſible for him to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance in his way, who keeps no certain
path?</p>
                     <p>WE muſt cure our ſelves of that raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and
inadvertency, which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend our actions. Certainly the Thing upon
which our Eternal Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Everlaſting Miſery depends, is well
worth our moſt ſerious Conſideration. We muſt furniſh our Hearts with
<hi>Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims</hi> of <hi>Piety,</hi> and purſue them with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
earneſtneſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99726:39"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM II.</hi> That it imports us in, the firſt
place, to examine what our Chief and Laſt End is.</head>
                     <p>THE firſt Act of Wiſdom is, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how we came into
the World; whether by an Effect of Chance, or that we owe our Being to the
Almighty Hand of GOD, who created us.</p>
                     <p>THE Second; Whether we ought to govern our ſelves by Rules;
or, without any the leaſt reflection or reſtraint, may give way to all the
thoughts of our Hearts, the words of our Mouths, and the works of our
Hands.</p>
                     <p>AND laſtly, the Chief Act of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is, to conſider
what we ought to be, and how to behave our ſelves with reſpect to our
Laſt End. GOD having of his Goodneſs, created us, we muſt be entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſubject to Him. Let us therefore look upon our ſelves as made for Him, and
conſequently ſo direct the whole Courſe of our Life, that it may
contribute to his Glory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99726:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM. III.</hi> That in all our actions, we ought to
have a due regard to our Laſt End.</head>
                     <p>IT is moſt ſtrange and deplorable, to ſee the greateſt
part of Mankind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this Life, without a juſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and
knowledge of the End, for which they were brought into it. This ariſes either
from their never entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thoughts of the Matter, or neglecting to
acquaint themſelves with it throughly.</p>
                     <p>AND yet a more ſad thing it is, when after this Examination
and Knowledge had of our Laſt End, we do not act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to our
Informations and Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions thereupon. This cannot but ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our
Diſorders the more inexcuſable, and make our Sins to cry the louder for
Vengeance.</p>
                     <p>WE muſt have a continual regard to our Laſt End, that ſo
it may regulate all the actions of our Life, and make us truly wiſe. But how
can we think of it, as we ought, without telling our ſelves, that our not
minding this, muſt needs be our ruin?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99726:40"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM IV.</hi> That we ought to conſider we are God's
Creatures.</head>
                     <p>SOME few years ſince, I had no Exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, and now I find
I have a Being, Life, Motion, a Rational Soul, Inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Mind, and a Body
more perfect, than that of any other Animal.</p>
                     <p>ALL Creatures adminiſter continual Supplies to my VVants;
the Heavens afford me their Lights and Influence; the Earth yields me her
Fruits, Waters and Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; the Creatures ſhe abounds with, ſerve for my
Food, Neceſſity and Delight.</p>
                     <p>SHALL I be excuſable then, if I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get HIM, who made me?
No, I muſt love Him with all my Soul, obey Him with all Faithfulneſs, and
in conſideration of theſe his Benefits heap'd upon me, bleſs and magnify
his Great Name. Theſe are Duties we ſhall find to be abſolutely
indiſpenſable, if we do but ſeriouſly conſider we are his
Creatures.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99726:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM V.</hi> That we ought to be moſt ſenſible
of God's Favour in our Preſervation.</head>
                     <p>WE muſt leave it to <hi>Atheiſts</hi> to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their
Subſiſtence, as they do their Being, to Chance; As for our part, we ought
to look upon our <hi>Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> as a continual Creation; ſince
GOD, by his Power, Goodneſs and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, communicates Life to us every
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                     <p>THERE is not one inſtant of our Life, but GOD delivers us
from infinite Evils, which, but for his Preventing Han, dwould moſt certainly
deſtroy us; who to this is pleas'd to ſuperadd ſuch plenty of
Bleſſings, as to make our Life. moſt ſweet and comfortable.</p>
                     <p>HOW thankful therefore ought we to be? How great
acknowledgments ought we to return to GOD, for theſe ſignal Favours to us?
Shall not we therefore, as often as we reſpire, meditate on Him, who ſo
conſtantly thinks of us?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99726:41"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM VI.</hi> That we ſhould continually reflect
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Great Work of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                     <p>HE who made, and does ſtill preſerve me, is the ſame,
who has redeemed me. It is neither Man, nor Angel, but the Only Son of GOD,
JESUS CHRIST Himſelf, who was willing to become my Surety, and appeaſe the
Wrath of his Almighty Father, in dying for me.</p>
                     <p>WHAT Outrages, what Torments, did not he ſuffer! He was
crucified like a Slave, and underwent a Puniſhment, that GOD Himſelf had
call'd a Curſe. Not only the World and Hell inſulted over Him, but He
complain'd of his being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken even of his Father.</p>
                     <p>O WHAT a ſtrange and horrible thing is Sin, that JESUS
CHRIST muſt ſhed his Blood to deliver me from it! What Profaneneſs! What
Sacriledge is it, to trample under Foot that Precious Blood, with which we are
redeem'd! How helliſhly wicked muſt we be, not to love a SAVIOUR, who ſo
dearly lov'd us!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99726:42"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM VII.</hi> That we muſt follow the Divine
Call.</head>
                     <p>'TIS GOD draws us, that we may come to Him; without which we
could not have the leaſt thought or deſire thitherward. We muſt obey his
Voice, while He is pleas'd to direct it to us; For elſe, Life and Redemption
procur'd by Him, will be unprofitable to us.</p>
                     <p>HOW many Heathens have been without the Advantages we injoy!
How many Infidels and Idolaters have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of this Grace of Vocation,
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which a Man can never be converted! Shall we make them riſe up in
Judgment againſt us?</p>
                     <p>O THE wonderful Patience and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of GOD! who after a
thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Contempts of his Grace, receives us to Repentance; After many
obſtinate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtings of the Heavenly Inſpirations of his Spirit; is
yet pleas'd to continue his Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Call to us! Follow we then his Voice,
which invites us to the Supremeſt Good.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99726:42"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM VIII.</hi> That we muſt Study God's Conduct
to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us.</head>
                     <p>WE loſe the Benefit of the Mercies and Chaſtiſements,
GOD di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſes to us, while we are unacquainted with the Conduct He
obſerves towards his Children. Through our ignorance of this, we afflict our
ſelves with that which is Matter of Comfort, and make merry in the midſt of
Temptations.</p>
                     <p>HAD <hi>Joſeph</hi> underſtood GOD'S Leading, he would
have wept, when he found himſelf his Maſter's Favourite, and rejoyced, when
the accuſation of his luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Miſtreſs caſt him into that Priſon,
which advanc'd him to little leſs, than <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Throne.</p>
                     <p>THE Devil prompts us to judge of GOD'S Conduct according to
outward appearance. This is one of his moſt dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Deluſions. It is
therefore our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to meditate upon thoſe <hi>Maxims,</hi> GOD has revealed
to us, and upon the Examples of his Providence towards the Saints, who have
been before us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:99726:43"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM IX.</hi> That we ought daily to examine our
Conſcience.</head>
                     <p>NOT to reflect upon our Behaviour, is to live without
<hi>Reaſon;</hi> and not to remind our ſelves, every day, of the State of
our Hearts, is to live without <hi>Grace.</hi> We ought to take daily notice
what good we have omitted, and what evil we have done.</p>
                     <p>WE cannot be ſaved without the ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of Repentance,
without a through reſolution to amend what's amiſs, and an anxious
ſeeking after thoſe Remedies that can heal us. VVhich is not attaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
but by a conſtant Review of our Thoughts, Words and Actions.</p>
                     <p>WE daily behold our ſelves in our Glaſs, and yet are
careleſs of conſulting the Law of GOD. 'Tis to undervalue the Study of
Perfection, thus to neglect our own Hearts, and bring our ſelves to that
paſs; as not to pray any more out of a ſenſe of our needs, but out of
meer Cuſtom.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:99726:43"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM X.</hi> That we ought to avoid too much
Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs.</head>
                     <p>A SOUL taken up with the Cares of Salvation, does not cumber
her ſelf with the things of this preſent Life. The retirement (which ſhe
conſecrates to to God, by devoting it to Pious Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) is much dearer
to her, than all the Employments in the World.</p>
                     <p>LET us remember the Parable of Our Lord, which aſſures us,
that the Word falling into the Heart of a Man, diſtracted with worldly Cares,
is like Seed that falls among Thorns, which growing up, choak it at laſt.</p>
                     <p>MY GOD! How much more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous is it, by means of a calm
and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed temper of Mind, to reſemble that good Ground, which brings
forth Thirty, Sixty, yea, even an Hundred Fold; than to have our Hearts crouded
with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand vain Solicitudes, how innocent ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may appear to
us!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99726:44"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XI.</hi> That we muſt often recollect our
ſelves, to think of our Salvation.</head>
                     <p>THE greateſt part of our Life is ſpent in a guilty kind of
Slumber. Time flies away, and the Glaſs of Life ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens to wards Death. We
come, we go, we talk and act; and this almoſt continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, without having
the leaſt regard to what concerns Salvation.</p>
                     <p>IF we judge aright, we ſhall find, that either we do that
which is altogether e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, or at leaſt, very remote from the Principal End of
Life; or elſe we Squan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our time in idleneſs, and do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.
Which neglect, though it be leaſt criminal, yet is not quite
fault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
                     <p>WE can make no better uſe of our Life, than when by frequent
retirement, we renew the Pious Reſolutions we have formerly taken. We muſt
examine very narrowly, whether our Life and Actions are anſwerable to that
Model we have ſet before us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99726:44"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XII.</hi> That we ought carefully to conſider
the Vanity of this Life.</head>
                     <p>THERE is nothing more miſerable, than Life's inconſtancy.
Its longeſt Date is but a Span. It is obnoxious to many thouſand accidents,
that ſnatch it away, when we leaſt think on't. It is more brittle, than
Glaſs; and at beſt but our way to Death,</p>
                     <p>AND can we thus reflect upon the Vanity of this Life, and not
be diſguſted? Can we help deſpiſing the pleaſures of it, and lifting
our Hearts above Time, fix them on the Life Eternal?</p>
                     <p>THE World paſſes away, and we in it: Its Deluſions, that
have ſo often ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized us, ſcatter and vaniſh, proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably to the
growth of our Experience. They only have attain'd a ſix'd and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
State, who have reſign'd themſelves to <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Contemplation
of Eternity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:99726:45"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XIII.</hi> That we ought frequently to think of
Death.</head>
                     <p>WE cannot avoid <hi>Death;</hi> But the time, place, manner,
and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of it, we know not. How great would be our Unhappineſs,
ſhould it ſurprize us in Sin and Impenitence, and come to execute the
dreadful Decree of our Everlaſting Damnation!</p>
                     <p>THE very image of Death affrights us, though we ſuppoſe it
afar off. What will it do, when it ſhall ſtare us in the Face, and ſet
before our Eyes our great and innumerable Sins, in oppoſition to
<hi>GOD'S</hi> Favours, and ſill our Souls with Remorſe and Terrour?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>GOD</hi> makes uſe of this Proſpect of the Grave to
affright us to him. It a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakens our Conſciences, fortifies our Faith, and
animates our Hopes. But Good <hi>GOD!</hi> VVhat would become of us, ſhould
we deſcend to Death without having once thought of, or conſider'd it, and
without being made wiſer by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions it affords?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:99726:45"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XIV.</hi> That we ought to conſider every Day,
as if it were our laſt.</head>
                     <p>JESUS CHRIST has commanded us, to watch conſtantly for his
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to judge the World. <hi>GOD</hi> has left us uncertain of the Hour of
our Death. What would not we wiſh we had done, if this very Day CHRIST
ſhould come to Judgment, or Death ſnatch us away, and ſet us before GOD'S
Tribunal?</p>
                     <p>WE loſe opportunities of doing good, and embrace thoſe of
doing ill; becauſe we think we are ſure to live long, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent before
Death ſurprizes us. Strange blind Security!</p>
                     <p>I AM aſſur'd GOD will pardon me, if I truly repent before
the Day of my Death; but ſhould be ſtark mad to think of delaying the Duty
of Repentance, a Moment, ſince 'tis not impoſſible but that even that
very Moment may be my laſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99726:46"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XV.</hi> That we ought continually to ſet the
Judgment of God before our Eyes.</head>
                     <p>HOW terrible will the <hi>Judgment</hi> of GOD be to the
Wicked! CHRIST, whom they have outrageouſly abus'd, is to give Sentence;
their own Conſciences to be Witneſs againſt them, and the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil waits
for the word of Command to put it in Execution. No Grace now to be hoped for;
no room left for Repentance.</p>
                     <p>SECRET Thoughts, idle VVords, wavering Actions; All ſhall be
brought forth to Judgment. GOD'S Aſſiſtance, Patience and Benefits will
be our reproach. Sins committed, good Deeds omitted, Time loſt, and the like,
will be puniſhed. Excuſes, Prayers, Tears; All theſe will avail nothing
againſt the Juſtice of this Tribunal.</p>
                     <p>OH! How much ought the dread of this Judgment to come, to
poſſeſs our Minds! How can we ſleep in Sin quietly? Our Souls may each
moment be cited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne of GOD, there to be judg'd and ſentenc'd
to Eternal Pains.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:99726:46"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XVI.</hi> That the Conſideration of the
Torments of Hell ought to affright us to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</head>
                     <p>IF the Divine Favours prove too weak, to overcome our
Obſtinacy; yet (at leaſt) let the pains of Hell, terrify us into Endeavours
to prevent them.</p>
                     <p>LET our minds viſit this Abyſs of Miſery, where the
Sinner ſuffers, in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Senſe, Torments proportioned to his Crimes. He
has loſt GOD for ever, and is given up to Eternal Remorſe of
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
                     <p>Priſons, Dungeons, Racks have their Terrours. But what are
theſe to Hell? Eternal Darkneſs, unquenchable Fire, the preſence of
Devils, and the Damned; Lamentations, Howlings, Blaſphemies, Deſpair.
Theſe are but a rude Draught of that Region of Anguiſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:99726:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XVII.</hi> That the Glory of Heaven ought
power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to incite our Piety.</head>
                     <p>HEAVEN is the Lot of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; where the abſence of
all Evil, an unſpeakable fulneſs of Bleſſings, both for Body and Soul,
and a perfect fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of GOD, ſhall make up our Happineſs. JESUS CHRIST,
the Bridegroom, will there give Conſummation to our Joys.</p>
                     <p>NO more Temptations, no more Sins, no more Sufferings, no more
Fears; But Light in the Mind, Comforts in the Heart, Peace in the Conſcience,
a perfect Union of the Faithful in giving Eternal Thanks to God, in the
enjoyment of Felicity that ſhall have no end.</p>
                     <p>VVhat ought not we to do; what Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries ſhould not we be
content to ſuffer, to ſecure the hope of this Glory God has promis'd to us?
What Terrour ought to ſeize us, when we reflect upon our Sins, which (if not
repented of) will deprive us of it for ever?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99726:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XVIII.</hi> That we are always to ſtand in a
Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Fear.</head>
                     <p>CHRIST having told his Diſciples, that one of them would
betray him, they all trembled at the horror of this Crime, though there was but
one, that was to commit it.</p>
                     <p>Let us always be watchful againſt the inconſtancy of our
Nature. Who knows whether the Eye of GOD does not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that in our
Hearts, which is yet unknown to us? The Example of the <hi>Saints,</hi> ought
to inſpire us with a Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fear.</p>
                     <p>THE Fall of St. <hi>Peter</hi> was expiated by Tears of
Repentance. But how can he who conſiders on his failing, truſt to his own
Strength? The Looks of his Maſter infus'd the Motives to his Remorſe. But
CHRIST does not always afford his Gracious Countenance to thoſe, who
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and deny him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:99726:48"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XIX.</hi> That Sin is more to be fear'd than
Death.</head>
                     <p>SIN is Treaſon againſt the King of Heaven: 'Tis copying
from the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len Angels. It is the only Object of <hi>GOD'S</hi> Averſion. He
puniſh'd it without remedy, in thoſe Curſed Spirits. And who can caſt
up the Accounts of them, Sin ſends to Eternal Deſtruction?</p>
                     <p>IF Death could be ſeparated from the Curſe of GOD; If it
did conſiſt in a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Annihilation; Wicked Men ought to wiſh for it, as
a Cure of the Reproaches and Diſquiets of their own Conſciences. But alas!
it is quite another thing.</p>
                     <p>LET us therefore fear Sin more than Death it ſelf; Or
rather; Let the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Deluge, the Flames of <hi>Sodom,</hi> and all
other Exemplary Judgments upon harden'd Sinners, diſplay to us the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors
of Sin, and the Everlaſting Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment reſerv'd for it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99726:48"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XX.</hi> That we ought to fear GOD more than
Men.</head>
                     <p>WHAT blindneſs is it to fear Men, more than GOD! We bear
with patience, the wrongs done us by our Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, leaſt our Complaints
ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our Oppreſſion. But we too often offend the Weak,
notwithſtanding CHRIST'S Command to the contrary.</p>
                     <p>IT's eaſier to reſtrain our Anger a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our
Inferiours (as CHRIST re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires) than to endure injuries from Great Men. Why
ſhould we then kindle a Fire, which CHRIST would have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, when
the only fear of Men, makes us careful to extinguiſh the Fire they kindle in
us?</p>
                     <p>LET us therefore <hi>judge righteouſly;</hi> be aſham'd of
our imperfections, and bluſh at our doing leſs for the fear of the LORD
(that LORD we are ſo much bound to love) than for the fear of Men, who have
to Title like his, either to our fear or love.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:99726:49"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXI</hi> That the whole Courſe of our Life
ought to be a continual Study of Mortification.</head>
                     <p>SO horribly has Sin corrupted our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that unleſs we
take great care continually to reſtrain our inclinations to Evil, we ſhall
unavoidably fall into all manner of Vices.</p>
                     <p>UNLESS the Fleſh be mortify'd, it will rebel againſt the
Spirit. Unleſs we reſiſt our Paſſions, they will prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the Light of our Reaſon, and our Reaſon, unleſs enlight'ned, will
oppoſe GOD'S Law and our Duty.</p>
                     <p>LET us beware of thoſe things that flatter our Senſes, and
feed our Paſſions. Let us not ſuffer our Thoughts to wander, but govern
our Hearts and Minds, by bringing them into a due Subjection to Reaſon and
the Will of GOD.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:99726:49"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXII</hi> That we ought continually to ſtrive
a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrulineſs of Self-Love.</head>
                     <p>THE Prevalence of Self-love is the Source of Sin. We all
naturally aſpire to Happineſs; this is innocent; But we place Felicity
either in Riches, Honours or Pleaſures; which is our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake.</p>
                     <p>GOD does not forbid us to love our ſelves; for Self-love is
neceſſary to our Preſervation; But he charges us, not to love our
ſelves with a blind and unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable Love; that is, to love our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
better than our Soul; this Temporal, more than Eternal Life.</p>
                     <p>LET'S labour to rectify our Paſſions, by propoſing to
them due Objects, things truly Good, Solid Honours, and Riches that take not to
themſelves Wings. Let us believe GOD'S Deciſions concerning theſe, rather
than the Suggeſtions of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:99726:50"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXIII</hi> That we ought to reſiſt our
Paſſions.</head>
                     <p>THIS Life is a Scene of Combate, where though we are not
always fighting with our Enemies, or wild Beaſts, yet muſt ever be
contending againſt our Paſſions, that endeavour to uſurp the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion
of our Hearts.</p>
                     <p>IF we ſuffer any one of theſe to be the Miſtreſs of
our Soul, then Farewell Reaſon and Tranquillity. Then will both our Soul and
Body be expos'd to inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Dangers: An Eternal Death to both, muſt be the
portion of ſuch, as ſhall be ſubjected to this Tyranny.</p>
                     <p>BUT while we courageouſly oppoſe their aſſaults, we
ſecure our quiet, and are in the ſure way to Glory, whereof we have
foretaſts even in this Life, at leaſt a certain Hope ſhall crown the
Conflict.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:99726:50"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXIV.</hi> That we ought to bridle that Pride,
which is apt to reign in us.</head>
                     <p>THERE is nothing more difficult, than the freeing our ſelves
from Pride. Men are naturally in love with their own Worth, and proud of what
they poſſeſs. They love to be eſteem'd of others, delight to make a
ſhew of their Perfections. In a word, their ambition is to be thought and
conſider'd as wiſe, skilful and honeſt Men.</p>
                     <p>BUT nothing is more neceſſary, than to oppoſe a
Paſſion, which is the Mother of Boaſting, Vain-Glory, Obſtinacy,
Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and Hypocriſy. What ſafety can theſe hope for, when GOD
has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd, he reſiſts the Proud, and gives Grace to the humble?</p>
                     <p>LET us conſider the Cauſe of this Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The
<hi>Devil,</hi> who is King of the Children of Pride, has infuſed it into us.
Its Effects here below, fill Human Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with Troubles and Debate; and its
Eternal Effects hereafter, are the uniting us to him, and ſeparating us from
our LORD, who is Humility it ſelf.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:99726:51"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXV.</hi> That we ought to ſuppreſs all
deſires of becoming great.</head>
                     <p>EVERY Condition has its Comforts and Diſtaſts. The
reaſon why we deſire to riſe in the World, is, becauſe we have no mind
to know this Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> That no State is happy, but that of the
Virtuous, be their Condition what it will.</p>
                     <p>LET us not think ſo much of riſing and becoming great, as
of collecting Comfort from a troubleſome Life, and extracting Pleaſure from
Calamity. Let us free our ſelves from diſquiets; the Place we may aim at,
is no better than that we are in.</p>
                     <p>GOD has appointed every one of us his Place and Bounds.
Theſe he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd for us by our Birth, Wealth and Capacity: Let us not
preſume to quit or go beyond them; ſince we cannot do it, without violating
the Decrees of his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,</hi> and expoſing our ſelves to
mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Temptations.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:99726:51"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXVI.</hi> That Humility ought to be the Badge of
our Profeſſion.</head>
                     <p>THERE is no true <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<hi>Humility;</hi> It was this <hi>CHRIST</hi> taught us, by his <hi>Life</hi>
and <hi>Doctrine.</hi> How dare we aſſume the Name of
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> while we neglect to practiſe his
<hi>Precepts?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>WE ought therefore ingenuouſly to acknowledge our
weakneſs, and inſtead of making a ſhew of our Parts, or other Advantages,
and ſeeking the praiſe of Men, embrace all occaſions, which may abate and
mortify our Pride.</p>
                     <p>TO do this, we need no more, than reflect on what we are. We
come from nothing, and are Sinners into the bargain; The Advantages we
poſſeſs, are the fruit of the Divine Bounty, and we muſt one day give
an account for them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99726:52"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXVII</hi> That we ought to beware of
Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</head>
                     <p>HOW properly is <hi>Covetouſneſs</hi> call'd by St.
<hi>Paul,</hi> the <hi>Root of all Evil?</hi> Love of Riches makes us deal
unjuſtly with our Neighbour; It ſtifles all ſenſe of natural Affection,
and changes an Apoſtle of <hi>CHRIST</hi> into a Miniſter of the
<hi>Devil.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A SOUL that is eagerly inclin'd to the love of Riches,
expoſes it ſelf to a certain danger for an uncertain gain; it fears not
Eternal Deſtruction, ſo it may but ſatisfy its greedineſs. Behold here
the Quinteſſence of Blindneſs and Folly.</p>
                     <p>LET us dread to be poſſeſs'd of ſo vile a Paſſion,
which will not ſtick to prompt us to betray our LORD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<hi>Judas</hi> did not betray Him, for fear of Perſecution, but through love
of Mony; and the ſame will make <hi>CHRIST</hi> to deſtroy us, without
remedy, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo ſottiſhly ſought for Happineſs, in heaping up
a little ſhining Duſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:99726:52"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXVIII.</hi> That we ought to reſtrain the
motions of Anger.</head>
                     <p>ANGER disfigures a Man, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throning his Reaſon. It is the
riſe of Quarrels, Curſings and Blaſphemies. It begets Hatred and Revenge,
without conſidering Reaſon, Juſtice or the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Laws.</p>
                     <p>HOW dangerous is it to give up our ſelves to this
Paſſion, and follow the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of it! VVhat an horrible thing to be
tranſported upon every ſlight occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or charge GOD with our
diſaſters, and murmur againſt him, or brandiſh our fury againſt our
Neighbour?</p>
                     <p>LET us betimes reſiſt the Motions of Anger. Let us learn
to look upon our Miſeries as Chaſtiſements; and upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, as Trials
GOD lays upon us. If our Heart at any time, riſes in ſpight of us, let us
preſently recall our ſelves, and not ſuffer the Sun (according to the Law
of <hi>CHRIST</hi>) to go down upon our Wrath.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:99726:53"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXIX.</hi> That we muſt root Envy out of our
Hearts.</head>
                     <p>WHAT greater Madneſs, than to be griev'd at our Neighbour's
Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, as if his Happineſs muſt needs make us Miſerable! VVhat
Injuſtice to rejoyce at his Misfortunes, and inſult over him, or take
delight in his being caſt down! This Paſſion cannot poſſeſs a
Heart, that is not given up to the Devil.</p>
                     <p>IF we will not abhor Envy, becauſe it conſumes the
Envious, and tears him inwardly; or for its delighting in, and feeding it
ſelf with Filth and Ordure; Let us at leaſt hate it, as being the Source of
that deteſtable Crime the <hi>Jews</hi> commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in delivering up Our LORD
to Death.</p>
                     <p>O LET us ſtrangle this Monſter, and acquieſce in
<hi>GOD'S</hi> VVay of diſpenſing his Favours. Let us freely impart the
Proſperity he has given us, or beg of Him to ſupply our want of power, by
granting our deſires for the good of our Neighbour.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:99726:53"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXX.</hi> That we ought to bear Injuries with
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SOCRATES</hi> being ſtruck, would not revenge himſelf.
This Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Patience, ſeveral Heathens have imitated; Yea, they have
made it their Endeavour to conquer the malice of their Enemies with
kindneſs.</p>
                     <p>ALAS! How many <hi>Chriſtians</hi> may juſtly fear, that
the Benignity of a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then will aggravate their Condemnation? VVe are
<hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and as ſuch ſhould own this for a Maxim, <hi>That he
who does the injury, is the Wretch, not he who ſuffers by it.</hi> VVe are
the Diſciples of GOD, who forbids us all Self-revenge; and yet we are ready
every minute to thunder out our reſentments againſt others.</p>
                     <p>LET us in a word wiſely conſider, that we are Criminals,
who ſue for Pardon; that we are at the foot of the Throne, and under the Eyes
of a GOD, who has proclaimed to us, that <hi>Vengeance</hi> is his. Let us not
ſet light by his Preſence, his Voice and Dreadful Judgments.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:99726:54"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXI.</hi> That we muſt abhor all
Impurity.</head>
                     <p>VVE cannot juſtly pretend to the Glory of Angels, unleſs
we imitate their Purity. To follow the pleaſures of the Fleſh, hunt after
its Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, and cheriſh its filthy Deluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is to walk in the Path
of Damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                     <p>CAN we be convinc'd of theſe Truths, without being in love
with <hi>Chaſtity;</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out avoiding all dangerous occaſions, as
inticing Company and guilty Sloth, and without arming our ſelves againſt
the Fleſh, by Faſting and Mortification?</p>
                     <p>LET us make a Covenant with our Eyes, that they never open a
Door to any unclean Thoughts; and if at any time they break this Covenant, let
our Heart, being animated by the Croſs of JESUS, ſtifle all thoſe
Thoughts in their Birth, which might lead us to Sin.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:99726:54"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXII.</hi> That we ought to beware of
Detraction.</head>
                     <p>DETRACTION is the Character of Malignity. VVe cannot revile
another, without hurting our ſelves, and them that take delight to hear us.
VVe make them Complices in our Sin; and by inſpiring them with the ſame
Hatred we have for our Neighbour, rob them of their Reſt.</p>
                     <p>VVE juſtly hold it ſinful to ſtain our Hands in our
Brother's Blood; and can we think it innocent to dip our Tongue in it by
Calumny, by publiſhing his faults, by rendring his Principles doubtful, or
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying his Virtues?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DAVID</hi> declares he could not abide Slanderers in
hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Court. Can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
CHRIST will admit them into Heaven, who blaſt their Brothers Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and
take delight in this kind of Cruelty?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:99726:55"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXIII.</hi> That we ought never to believe
Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to the prejudice of Truth.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PILATE</hi> perceiving the malice of the <hi>Jews,</hi>
and the Innocence of CHRIST, would fain have cleared Him; but was vanquiſhed
by a Motive of Carnal Policy. He no ſooner heard them cry out [<hi>If thou
releaſe this Man, thou art not</hi> Caeſar's <hi>Friend</hi>] but his
pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of ſaving Him vaniſh'd.</p>
                     <p>O INJUSTICE! VVas CHRIST ever a Head of Rebels? Did He at any
time, provide Arms and Ammunition, or levy Souldiers? Did not He ſubmit
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the <hi>Roman</hi> Laws, pay Tribute and openly aſſert
<hi>Caeſar's</hi> Right?</p>
                     <p>TO accuſe CHRIST of Sedition, was to call depth of Poverty,
Pride and Ambition; Obedience, Rebellion, and Humility, Vain-Glory. But
Pretences are never wanting, and depraved Nature lends a more willing Ear to
<hi>Calumny,</hi> than <hi>Truth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:99726:55"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXIV.</hi> That we ought to weigh the
Conſequences both of Vice and Virtue.</head>
                     <p>VIRTUE is laid aſide, when the difficulties of it only are
conſider'd, and <hi>Vice</hi> embrac'd when the Pleaſures it yields are
ſet before us. But a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> ought to make very different
Reflections.</p>
                     <p>VIRTUE bears an Impreſſion of GOD, and <hi>Vice</hi> is
the Fruit of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's</hi> Suggeſtions. The former fills the Soul
with Tranquillity, by begetting in it the Love of GOD and <hi>Men;</hi> And the
latter Galls the Conſcience with a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Checks, and brings the
Offender into contempt both with GOD and Men.</p>
                     <p>BUT above all, a good Man expects with joy, the Glory of
Heaven, which he is to poſſeſs; whereas the Wicked are continually rack'd
with the fears of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Torments, which GOD has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be their
portion for ever. Who after theſe Reflections, can remain doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful where to
chooſe?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:99726:56"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXV.</hi> That we ought to make a careful
Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny into our Defects, in order to our Amendment.</head>
                     <p>RELIGION invites us to the Study of Perfection; It ſets
before us GOD and CHRIST for our <hi>Pattern;</hi> It furniſhes us with
infinite Motives to ingage us to it, and gives us to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that our
<hi>Happineſs</hi> conſiſts in this <hi>Perfection.</hi> How is it then
that we labour not after it?</p>
                     <p>WE read, ſpeak, write, diſcourſe it morally, and talk of
our Paſſions and their Remedies; And yet continue in the ſame State,
ſtill have the ſame Vices and Inclinations; And all is, becauſe we do not
apply our ſelves to a through-ſearch of our Hearts.</p>
                     <p>OUR Faults can never be amended, unleſs they be known; nor
known, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out enquiry. The Heart, which is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious in ſearch
after the Frailties of others, to upbraid them therewith, would be better
employ'd, in examining and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying <pb n="99" facs="tcp:99726:56"/>Remedies to its own.
This is a chief Ingredient towards the attainment of Perfection.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="maxim">
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXVI.</hi> That we ought not to make Cuſtom,
or Example, a Plea for our Faults.</head>
                     <p>THOUGH <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> does not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us to ſhun
<hi>Human Society,</hi> yet its chief aim is, to inculcate to us, that the
<hi>World</hi> is plung'd in Sin and Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and therefore that we
ought not to imitate its corrupt Manners.</p>
                     <p>WORLDLY Men find delight in thoſe actions that offend GOD.
They provoke one another, by their Examples, to violate the Divine Laws,
without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret or reſtraint. But we muſt reject their impious Maxims, that
we may follow the Law of GOD.</p>
                     <p>WHAT folly then is it to make theſe our Patterns? Do we
think that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of their Examples and Cuſtoms, can over-rule
the Divine Right and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over us?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:99726:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXVII.</hi> That we muſt avoid Relapſes into
Sin.</head>
                     <p>WHAT miſerable Wretches are we, to condemn our Repentance,
and return to the Way of Perdition, whence GOD by his Grace has recalled us!
What elſe is this, but to precipitate our ſelves into remedileſs Woes, by
a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous contempt of GOD'S Favours, and our own Salvation?</p>
                     <p>LET us therefore retain in our Hearts a true ſorrow for
having offended the DIVINE MAJESTY, be afraid of the Actions that firſt
prompted us to ſin, and careful to make uſe of thoſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies
GOD</hi> has provided for us, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and perfect our <hi>Cure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>IS the Health of the <hi>Soul</hi> of leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern to us,
than that of the <hi>Body?</hi> Or are the Eternal pains, which GOD will
inflict upon them, who ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be carry'd away with the
Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of their Paſſions, incapable to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright us to Him?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:99726:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXVIII.</hi> That we muſt not abuſe the
Long-Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering of God.</head>
                     <p>STRANGE and ſurprizing is the Corruption of our Nature!
GOD'S <hi>Patience,</hi> which ſo meekly invites us to Repentance, ſerves
but to harden us in our wicked Ways; The greater his <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency</hi> is
towards <hi>us,</hi> the more we multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply our Tranſgreſſions againſt
Him.</p>
                     <p>WHILE we cannot be ignorant, that his Patience admits of
Bounds, and that the End of his Mercy is the Beginning of an inexorable
Severity. We heap up to our ſelves <hi>a Treaſure of Wrath,</hi> in
refuſing to comply with the Gracious Invitations of <hi>DIVINE LOVE.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>WHEN therefore we reflect upon his <hi>Forbearance</hi>
towards us, while we were diſobedient, let us, by no means, thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,
that we may ſtill continue to abuſe it; but remember, that <hi>Patience
provok'd turns into Fury.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:99726:58"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XXXIX.</hi> That we muſt not be aſhamed of
God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</head>
                     <p>THE moſt terrible Temptation we are lyable to, is to ſee
the Modiſh Men of the Age, call the <hi>Fear</hi> of <hi>GOD
Superſtition,</hi> and <hi>Devotion Hypocriſy.</hi> They endeavour to
perſwade us, that none but baſe and abject Minds are capable of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
beſotted with ſuch <hi>Chymaera</hi>'s.</p>
                     <p>HAD Worldly Men a Heaven to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward our complying with their
Opinions, and a Hell to avenge the Contempt of their Maxims, it were worth our
At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
                     <p>BUT alas! What Fools are we? The reſpect we have for them,
proves fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal to us. It is madneſs, not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of imitating their
Crimes, and to bluſh when we tranſgreſs their Rules, in purſuance of
our Duty.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:99726:58"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XL.</hi> That a faint and languiſhing
<hi>Piety</hi> is a miſerable State.</head>
                     <p>WHAT do we pretend by our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſneſs, and fainting in the
Way of <hi>Godlineſs?</hi> Is not <hi>GOD</hi> Worthy to be belov'd, and
ſerv'd with our beſt Zeal? Or what Comforts can we hope to reap from cold
Devotion?</p>
                     <p>TO eat at CHRIST'S Table, be in his Service, and at the ſame
time hide the <hi>Talent</hi> he has intruſted us with, and give up our
ſelves to ſloath and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence; What is this, but a Contempt of his
Grace, and a Provocation for his with drawing it?</p>
                     <p>THOUGH GOD may ſeem to bear with thoſe, who are without
any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion at all of his <hi>Grace;</hi> yet certain it is, that He
cannot endure the <hi>Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm.</hi> The unconcern'dneſs theſe have for
Him, forcibly provokes his Averſion. He that loves truly, looks upon
<hi>Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>Lukewarmneſs,</hi> as High Treaſon againſt
<hi>Love.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:99726:59"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLI.</hi> That we muſt continue in the
Exerciſe of <hi>Piety.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DAS</hi> had been ſaved, if nothing were requir'd to
<hi>Godlineſs,</hi> but noble and daring Beginnings. We muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in
well-doing. <hi>He that holds out to the End, ſhall be Sav'd.</hi> Without
this <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> no Grace, no Glory, no Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation is to be hop'd
for.</p>
                     <p>LET us not perſiſt in GOD'S Service in the time of
Proſperity only, or while we have no occaſion to follow our Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions,
or ſo long as our Heart does not find ought in our Duty, that thwarts its
Inclinations.</p>
                     <p>LET us with faithfulneſs and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, apply our
ſelves to the Practiſe of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> It had been much better
for the Damned, never to have entred into the VVay of
<hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> than being once entred, to depart from it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:99726:59"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLII.</hi> That we muſt make the Holy Scripture
the Subject of our continual Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
                     <p>IN <hi>Prayer</hi> we ſpeak to GOD; and in the
<hi>Scripture</hi> GOD ſpeaks to us. Do we think GOD will hear us when we
ſpeak to Him, if we neglect to hear, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully meditate upon what he
tells us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Authority over us, and our Duty towards Him?</p>
                     <p>THE <hi>Scripture</hi> contains the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Truths
we can know, the wiſeſt Maxims we can follow in our Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the
greateſt Promiſes we can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; And yet miſerable VVretches that we
are, we neglect to apply our ſelves to the reading of it.</p>
                     <p>WHAT? If this Priviledge were forbidden us, ſhould not we
look upon ſuch Prohibition, as the greateſt of our Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes? And
while we enjoy that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of making it the Subject of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation day
and night, ſhall we be ſo unjuſt, as to read it perfunctorily, and be
ignorant of its moſt important Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:99726:60"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLIII.</hi> That we ought carefully to apply our
ſelves to Prayer.</head>
                     <p>WE can't <hi>live</hi> well, unleſs we know how to
<hi>pray</hi> well; And there is no Happineſs, but in Conjunction with a Good
Life. <hi>Holineſs</hi> is that which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes GOD; and fervent
<hi>Prayer</hi> obtains us the <hi>Fruits</hi> of his <hi>Love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>PRAYER is the moſt eaſie part of our Duty; Our Needs teach
it us; It is the moſt Auguſt and Honourable, in that it procures us a
familiar Converſe with GOD Himſelf. It is alſo the moſt bliſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful;
for it opens us the Treaſures of Heaven, and Communicates to us every
<hi>Divine Bleſſing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>SHOULD we be debarr'd the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of it, we ſhould hold it
for Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as it would be an impediment to our Felicity and Glory. How then
can we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervalue the Duty of Prayer, as an unprofitable thing?</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:99726:60"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLIV.</hi> That we muſt always have our Holy
Baptiſm before our Eyes.</head>
                     <p>BAPTISM is the Token of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into Covenant with GOD.
In it GOD has offer'd us the Pardon of our Sins, the Guidance of his Grace, and
the Hope of his Glory; And we on our part, have promis'd to forſake our
Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, ſubmit our ſelves to his Laws, and be faithful to Him unto
Death.</p>
                     <p>DO we think it juſt, <hi>GOD</hi> ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his
Promiſes, when we forget thoſe we have made Him in that Holy Sacrament?
Does not this Forgetfulneſs favour of Contempt, Unbelief; nay, and Rebellion
it ſelf?</p>
                     <p>LET us therefore always ſet before our Eyes our own
Engagements, as well as our Hopes; our Duty, as well as the Grace <hi>GOD</hi>
freely offers; our Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to live according to the Rules of
Chriſtianity, as well as the Glory <hi>GOD</hi> has annex'd to it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:99726:61"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLV.</hi> That we ought to remember the
Promiſes we make to GOD at our Receiving the Lord's Supper.</head>
                     <p>WE are from our Infancy, entertain'd in God's Service, wherein
we were ingag'd before we knew the Reward. But we do make a ſolemn Choice of
it, in our own Perſons, when we preſent our ſelves at the <hi>HOLY
TABLE.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>COMMON Senſe alone would not ſuffer us to do a Thing of
ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, without a ſerious conſideration of the Duties it lays
upon us. It were better never to participate of this <hi>Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
than to do it unprepared and unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably.</p>
                     <p>THE Sacred <hi>Euchariſt</hi> repreſents to us the
Expiation of our Crimes, and the Horror of them, the ineffable Love of GOD, and
the infinite Obligations and Ties we have to CHRIST. To ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach his Table,
without bewailing and forſaking our Sins, without loving and devoting our
ſelves to Him, is to receive our own Damnation.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:99726:61"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLVI.</hi> That Charity is to be preferr'd before
all things.</head>
                     <p>THERE is nothing more valuable with GOD, than
<hi>Charity.</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came <hi>Man,</hi> that He might the more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually
preſcribe this Duty to us, and ſuffer'd <hi>Death,</hi> to give us the
moſt engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Example of this <hi>Divine Virtue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>HE began the Choice of his Diſciples with calling two
Brothers. And why ſo? But to intimate, that Brotherly Love muſt unite all
his Diſciples, and Concord be the Badge of <hi>Chriſtianity?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>WHAT can we with Juſtice prefer before <hi>Love?</hi> Yea,
what ought not we to do and ſuffer, what Care ſhould not we take, rather
than violate the Laws of <hi>Charity?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:99726:62"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLVII.</hi> That we ought to prevent the
Petitions of thoſe, who are in Miſery.</head>
                     <p>THIS <hi>poor</hi> Wretch is our own Fleſh and Blood, our
Brother; GOD having made, and <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST</hi> redeemed him. How careful
therefore ought we to be, to relieve his <hi>Neceſſities? GOD</hi>
Himſelf is pleas'd to become ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to us for our Liberality, and
CHRIST will make it an everlaſting Reward.</p>
                     <p>OUR Brethren's <hi>Miſery</hi> ſhould the more recommend
them to us. But if that be too weak to move our Pity, at leaſt let the
Bleſſed Fruits of <hi>Charity,</hi> and the Example of JESUS CHRIST,
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage us to the Practice of a Duty ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and full of
Bliſs.</p>
                     <p>MUST the Money we ſo unjuſtly hoard up, prove our own
Accuſer? JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST has told us he will take the good we do to thoſe who
ſtand in need of it, as done to Himſelf; And yet we don't run to prevent
their asking. Is this our Love to <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Salvation?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="48" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:99726:62"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM. XLVIII.</hi> That we muſt be meek in reproving
our Neighbour.</head>
                     <p>GOD aſſures us, that one of the moſt conſiderable
Effects of Love is to <hi>reprove</hi> our <hi>Neighbour,</hi> when he ſins.
And indeed, we have no true Love for him, if we don't endeavour to divert him
from the way that leads to Death. Beſides, this good Office alſo engages us
the more forcibly to our own Duty.</p>
                     <p>THOUGH it be lawful to uſe either mild or ſevere
Expreſſions, according as it may beſt ſuit with the good of our
<hi>Neighbour;</hi> yet Sweetneſs and Sincerity muſt always be predominant
in our Hearts towards him; remembring that GOD's Cauſe is the Diſpute: And
He is <hi>Love</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                     <p>LET us <hi>reprove</hi> our <hi>Neighbour</hi> with all
tenderneſs; and if we do it more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at leaſt let nothing of
bitterneſs or paſſion appear in our Words. As Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity puts us upon this
Duty; ſo let us by <pb n="112" facs="tcp:99726:63"/>our manner of doing it, perſwade
him, it is our Love for him, and not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of inſulting over him, that
is the Motive.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:99726:63"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM XLIX.</hi> That Practice is to be preferr'd
before Knowledge or Words.</head>
                     <p>WE ought, with all earneſtneſs, to meditate upon, and
labour to make our ſelves throughly acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Law of GOD. We
muſt apply our ſelves to the Study of Heavenly Myſteries; and to that
End, be frequent in the reading and Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Holy
Scripture.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>IT is our Duty to edify our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, with our good
Diſcourſe, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him in <hi>Piety.</hi> What greater joy, than to
be able to impart our Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to him! Which ſtill encreaſes as it is
Communicated: And we, at the ſame time, have the honour of being employ'd by
GOD, to advance the <hi>Salvation</hi> of his Children.</p>
                     <p>AFTER all, What Fruit can we pretend to reap from all our
Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Rhetorick, if the Acts of a Spiritual Life be not exerted by us? 
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:99726:64"/>What an horrible thing is it to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light'ned, and
ſpeak like Angels, and yet live like <hi>Devils!</hi> Knowledge ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate
from a good Conſcience, does but ſerve to aggravate our Crimes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="maxim">
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:99726:64"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>MAXIM L.</hi> That we ought to impute all that is good
in us, to the Grace of God.</head>
                     <p>THERE is nothing but the <hi>Devil</hi> can make us attribute
ought to our ſelves in the Work of our <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi> We are born in
Sin, live in Sin, and ſhould die in Sin, did not GOD'S Grace prevent us.</p>
                     <p>OUR <hi>Call</hi> to <hi>Faith,</hi> is the Work of his
<hi>Grace;</hi> Our <hi>Converſion,</hi> the Work of his <hi>Spirit,</hi>
which overcomes our Averſion; Our <hi>Perſeverance</hi> is the Effect of
the ſame <hi>Holy Spirit.</hi> The Beginning, Progreſs and End of our
<hi>Salvation,</hi> are deriv'd from <hi>Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>LET us Confeſs the Truth; If we cannot aſſume ought to
our ſelves, but Miſery, Corruption, Love to Sin, and <pb n="116" facs="tcp:99726:65"/>Enmity to GOD'S Law, we muſt look upon GOD, as the Sole
<hi>Author</hi> of our <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and accordingly aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe all
the Glory of it to <hi>Him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:99726:65"/>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
